<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An iron rod put into the Lord Protectors hand, to break all antichristian powers in pieces. Or, A discourse, which tends to a spirituall war with all sects and self-opinions, which are the Churches enemies: wil bring Englands everlasting happiness, and joyn all other lands into the body of Christs Church, to serve God with with [sic] one consent, Zeph. 3.9. All which was discovered to John Sanders of Harburn, neer Brimingham [sic]: by true apparitions, revelations, and many several visions, as the second book sheweth.</title>
            <author>Sanders, John, of Harburn.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93935</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E842_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203488</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863433</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863433</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115635</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93935)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115635)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 128:E842[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An iron rod put into the Lord Protectors hand, to break all antichristian powers in pieces. Or, A discourse, which tends to a spirituall war with all sects and self-opinions, which are the Churches enemies: wil bring Englands everlasting happiness, and joyn all other lands into the body of Christs Church, to serve God with with [sic] one consent, Zeph. 3.9. All which was discovered to John Sanders of Harburn, neer Brimingham [sic]: by true apparitions, revelations, and many several visions, as the second book sheweth.</title>
                  <author>Sanders, John, of Harburn.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 67, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold at the Angel in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 17".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115635:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN IRON ROD PUT INTO The Lord PROTECTORS Hand, To break all Antichriſtian Powers in pieces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> A Diſcourſe, which tends to a Spirituall War with all Sects and Self-opinions, which are the Churches enemies: wil bring <hi>Englands</hi> everlaſting happineſs, and joyn all other Lands into the body of Chriſts Church, to ſerve God with with one conſent, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.9.</p>
            <p>All which was diſcovered to <hi>John Sanders</hi> of <hi>Harburn,</hi> neer <hi>Brimingham:</hi> By true Apparitions, Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and many ſeveral Viſions, as the ſecond Book ſheweth.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Thou ſhalt break them with a rod of iron, and daſh them in pieces like a Potters veſsel,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 2.9. Rev. 2.27.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>The Lords voice cryeth unto the City, and the man of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhall ſee my name: hear the rod, and who hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Micah. 6.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be ſold at the Angel in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:115635:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115635:2"/>
            <head>The Table of the Second Book.</head>
            <p>THis Second Book of <hi>John Saunders</hi> ſheweth a true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation how and where he was called at noon-time of the day, on the 11. day of <hi>June</hi> 1643. by a true and a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible apparition; and further how the Lord revealed his ſecret intent, and confirmed it to him by true ſigns, and ſhewed him the greateſt remarkable revolutions, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, chances, and changes, as have been ever ſince be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween King and Parliament, which he then declared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many: And what way the Church ſhal be re-buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to bring all Lands into one Chriſtian Body, and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Eaith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Surely ſaith the Lord, then will I turne to the people a pure language, that they may call upon the name of the Lord, and ſerve him with one conſent,</hi> Zephany 3.9.</p>
            <p>And a true Relation of what horrible afflictions God ſuffered him to be ſundry and many times caſt into by Satan and his inſtruments, becauſe he did at firſt neglect the meſſage of the Lord of Hoſts, conterning King and Parliament, Church and State.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>IN this Second Book of</hi> John Sanders, <hi>here is ſhewn a true Relation of the manner how God called me to this work in as wonderful a way as he did</hi> Paul, <hi>at noon-time of the day, by an open apparition, on the</hi> 11. <hi>day of</hi> June 1643.</p>
            <p>Page 37</p>
            <p>As I was employed in a Faire with my Maſter, Mr. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Bloomer,</hi> it pleaſed my heavenly Maſter and Father in Chriſt, to cauſe me to ſee the Apparition then at that immediate time: But God knowing that I was inclined by nature to be hard of beliefe, like <hi>Thomas,</hi> who would not believe unles he felt and ſaw both; or like the men of our late dayes, which will not believe but that Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Revelations, and true Viſions are now ceaſed, it pleaſed God to convert me from that erroneous unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb facs="tcp:115635:3"/>mind, in as wonderful a manner as he did <hi>Paul</hi> at noon-time of the day, and cauſed me to feele his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, as the reading of this Book wil tel you in what manner; and at noon again four dayes after, how the Lords holy Angel was ſent to comfort my comfortleſſe condition by ſecret and ſtrange Revelation, and on the morrow at night after, and on the next morning, being <hi>Friday,</hi> the 17. day, to confirm me by trial, and terrible Viſions, and ſtrange temptations, and then to comfort me with his holy Angel, &amp; to give me a command to goe to King and Parliament, as it were to be a Herauld of Armes, or heavenly Embaſſador from the King of Kings.</p>
            <p>And to tel firſt the King what would befal him unleſs ſuch things were agreed on as this Book ſheweth; and then to go to the Parliament to ſhew what they muſt do, or elſe the like and worſe judgment would befal them at laſt, unleſs they would do as <hi>Zacheus</hi> did when Chriſt called him: Yet the Kings Son, and a remnant of them; muſt and would agree at laſt; for upon their agreement is the greateſt meanes under God to call the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and convert the whole world into one union of Faith.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>I</hi> was ſhewed what miſery <hi>I</hi> was to undergoe if I refuſed to goe on Gods meſſage, yet muſt go at laſt. This book of my troubles ſheweth the manner what I have endured.</p>
            <p>Firſt, of my going to ſpeak with the King when he was priſoner at <hi>Holmby,</hi> and in what manner I was prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from ſpeaking with the King himſelf, and then what <hi>I</hi> told Colonel <hi>Graves</hi> would befal firſt to the King, and then the Parliament, if ſuch things were not done as this Book ſpeaks of; and what great troubles befel me after by Satans malicious working againſt me, by my wife and her kindred and ſome of my own, and many wicked men beſides, and of Gods great miraculous deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance and mercy to me. <hi>p.</hi> 44, 46, 47, 48</p>
            <p>Secondly, of my putting out of a little Book about the time that the Levellers roſe againſt the Parliament, called <hi>A Deſcription of the Ten Commandements concerning this late
<pb facs="tcp:115635:3"/>War,</hi> laying open the miſery of the Church, by reaſon of covetous and new fangled Teachers were crept into it for want of true Church-government: And then what troubles befel me again, and how ſome of her friends ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged her to be divorced from me, and of their perſecuting of me. <hi>p.</hi> 54, 55</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Bill of Divorcement put in print in this Book, given her ſix yeares ſince after this manner, which ſhe and they were the cauſers of. <hi>p.</hi> 58</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the manner how God compelled me to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel <hi>Worceſter</hi> fight, and the manner and time of it, and how the King would be overthrown if he fought, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent witneſs produced that heard me ſpeak it. <hi>p.</hi> 62.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, the humble petition of <hi>Iohn Sanders</hi> to the Lord Protector, of his often comming to <hi>London</hi> ſince to ſpeak with the Parliament, to tel that Parliament that they could not ſtand, and to ſhew them what was the cauſe. Colonel <hi>Barkſtead</hi> can witneſſe it that God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled me to tel him, and what would be the cauſe. <hi>p.</hi> 53</p>
            <p>Sixthly, of my comming out of <hi>Ireland</hi> neer 6. weeks before the little Parliaments diſſolution, and to tel ſome of them that Gods decree was ſo gone out againſt them, that they would be diſſolved about the ſhorteſt day in the yeare: Witneſs Colonel <hi>Barkeſtead,</hi> which is now the Lieutenant of the Tower. And then of my going into our Country, of my being compelled by God to prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure &amp; declare in <hi>Brimingham</hi> what was then doing that day in <hi>London,</hi> 88. miles from <hi>London,</hi> &amp; then of my being thrown into priſon. <hi>p.</hi> 64</p>
            <p>Seventhly, of my being compelled by the dictates of Gods ſpirit to ſpeak and write many times, and make many journeys ſince to the preſent power, and the laſt Parliament, to tel them what hath and wil befal them, unleſſe they wil deny themſelves and ſeek God. <hi>p.</hi> 65</p>
            <p>Eightly, of ſeveral Viſions as I have had this yeare concerning the Church being rebuilded ſuddenly, and the Lord Protectors Councel and King <hi>Charles</hi> his agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:
<pb facs="tcp:115635:4"/>And how God revealed the plot of the Countrys-riſing to me, and cauſed me to carry a Letter to the Tower of it, and to deliver it before the riſing was. <hi>p.</hi> 66, 67</p>
            <p>Woe is me if I declare not faithfully that which the Lord declareth to me, either to King or Parliament:</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>Gourteous Reader, ſome Errours have eſcaped the preſse, yet but one worth obſervation. In page</hi> 38. <hi>line</hi> 32. <hi>for</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, <hi>read</hi> Wedneſday.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:115635:4"/>
            <head>The Table of the Firſt Book.</head>
            <p>FIrſt, here is ſhewed in this Book to your Highneſs, and all others that pleaſe to hear or read it, a Petition to move you with all expedition to goe about the work of God to finde out true Religion, for the beautifying of Gods Church, and then to build it up. <hi>Page 1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly; the manner and time how <hi>Davids</hi> Tabernacle fell, as well from the Chriſtian Gentiles which were in Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covenant, as it did from the <hi>12.</hi> Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boams</hi> time under the Law, and how there was never no true Religion in one body ſince they parted. <hi>p. 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, a ſhort deſcription of the Proteſtants ruinating in this land by this late war. <hi>p. 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the true manner deſcribed how <hi>Davids</hi> fallen Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle ſhould be begun to be raiſed as in the dayes of old, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos 9,</hi> proved by Law and Goſpel-rule to be the true Channel for the Church to run in firſt in this land; and no other way then this can be proved, which wil bring the whole world to one union of faith, to ſerve God with one conſent, <hi>Zeph. 3.9. p. 6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, what a wilderneſs &amp; infectious, poyſoned, and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered condition the Church and people of God are in for want of a Church-government, according to Patriarchal, Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, Apoſtolical, and Diſcipled orders, the true manner of which is laid down in this Book. <hi>p. 13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, true comparative ſignes, firſt by the Stars, ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Moon, that Chriſts true Religion is ready to breake forth into beautifulneſs more then ever it was in. <hi>p. 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, a godly direction and admonition for his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Lord Protector, to take the like care for the chuſing of a High Prieſt to be Head in chief for Chriſts Church, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> eldeſt ſervant did for a wife for <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the figure of Chriſt, <hi>Gen. 24.</hi> This wil be the beginning of a fifth Monarchy under Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Eightly, the manner of the High Prieſts receiving of the number of <hi>12.</hi> Apoſtolical Biſhops to be Head Fathers of the <hi>12.</hi> ſpiritual Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which are now ſcattered abroad, <hi>Jam. 1.</hi> by the holy order of laying on of hands, and of his and their receiving the number of <hi>70.</hi> under them, to make a body above the ordinary Miniſters of Chriſts Church, <hi>p. 22.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115635:5"/>
            <p>Ninthly, the true manner how to prove them whether their calling and election be of God or not, by going to a ſpiritual war, which is a contending for the faith, or caſting rods and lots with all Sects and ſelf-opinions, which are the Churches e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, <hi>Num. 17.18. Matth. 27.55. Joh. 19.23.</hi> Iude. <hi>p. 25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tenthly, the manner of the Whore of <hi>Babels</hi> fal, and all falſe forms in one day in this land to be a patterned example for the whole world to follow; and for the calling of the <hi>Jewes, Turks, Pagans,</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> to the true faith, <hi>p. 27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eleventhly, it ſheweth the glorious time of the new <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lems</hi> ſituated government, and of the Churches glory. <hi>p. 31</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Twelfthly, it ſheweth how that King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second-is appointed by God to be his chief King under Chriſt over the whole world; and the Lord Protector, if he will be obedient to the word of the Lord, to be the ſecond under him, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> faithful ſervant to be chief Ruler for the King; for by their agreement the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> are to be called. <hi>p. 36.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all that aſſiſt them, and are faithful in their places, that are now in power, and wil be obedient willingly now they ſee Gods truth and righteous peace ready to break forth, to yield to God and his true anointed King, if they loſe a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines place, Major, Colonel, or General, which now is held by troubleſome fear, then it wil be no more loſs to them then the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>attaining to a Knight, Lord, Judge, Earle, Duke, or Deputy, King or Prince, by this peaceable agreement, til the end of all things come to diſsolution over this Land and many more for them to be Governours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As</hi> I <hi>am commanded of God to threaten thoſe that have gotten into other mens poſſeſſions, contrary to godlineſs or good conſciences, and ſo prove themſelves by it to be enemies in that to Gods glorious Goſpel, and the Primitive Churches practice; ſo</hi> I <hi>am commanded of God to threaten all with the danger of their own ruine, and the diſpleaſure of God, that will not forbear plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and mutyning, and ſo hurt the Kings agreement. Doe you think it is poſſible to ſtand in a ſtrong wind, and throw chaff againſt the wind, and it not fly back upon you? Do you think it is poſſible to doe Gods work before his time be? It is but the Devils policie to cauſe you ſo to think. God is neer, ariſing to deliver his people, and to reſtore his Church: Therefore wait patiently till the time be, for the day is neer a dawning.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115635:5"/>
            <head>TO HIS HIGHNESSE the Lord PROTECTOR.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>MAy it pleaſe your Highneſs</hi> to vouchſafe the reading of this little Book, which God cauſed me your ſervant in the Lord <hi>Iohn Sanders,</hi> to indite unto you; who hath come oftentimes on purpoſe to ſpeake with you, being compelled by the power of the holy Ghoſt, (which enableth me to foretel things) to ſhew you what Gods wil is toward you, if you will believe and obey the Lord.</p>
            <p>O my Lord, wo is me if I be either fearful or negligent to give you and all others warning, ſince God hath called me, and ſhewed me a ſword of Juſtice which proceedeth out of his mouth, which he is now ariſing to draw forth, not onely againſt you and your power, but againſt all the chiefe gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the world, unleſſe ſpeedily you and they deny your own wayes and imbrace Gods wayes: Thoſe that ſo doe, it ſhal go wel with them.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I ſhal in theſe firſt lines forbeare making uſe of any other mens labours, ſtudy, or Scripture phraſes, leſt you ſhould rather think it to be brain knowledge then the dictates of Gods Spirit.</p>
            <p>I conceive your Highneſs believeth that where God appears by viſions, and Chriſt takes up the roome, the holy Ghoſt carrieth them on by a real true power. they wil be ſo gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ſhewed Gods waies and wil, according to their gift and talent, to write or ſpeak the mind of God without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtudy or natural parts, when God pleaſeth.</p>
            <p>The Scriptures are given of God to be as a touchſtone for them that feare God and obey his wil, to try the ſpirits whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115635:6"/>they be of God, therefore let them be your Judge; but have eſpecial care of wreſting them: endeavour to let them areſt you in this life, and you ſhal have reſt in the life to come: Truly, my Lord, if ſuch like counſel, which natural men wil not own, but count fooliſhneſs, doe not guide you, you wil not only ſtumble in points of Religion, as many doe to fall from heavenly things, but you wil fall from the high place that Gods providence hath raiſed you to. Which by yeelding obedience to God and his King Jeſus Chriſt, and him whom he wil ſet upon his holy mountain, you may ſtand firm; otherwaies it wil be very ſlippery.</p>
            <p>O for the Lords ſake, who hath ſet you up to be a prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of the people, endeavour to build your ſelf a ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: Imbrace this truth, take good heed to hold faſt the good old waies of Gods worſhip: but you muſt firſt finde it, for it hath been a long time loſt: take heed therefore of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſpiſing, or not believing and obeying the ſpirit of Gods propheſie.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I have had ſtil a great feare of you, but it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the love of God in Chriſt which bindeth me to fear, love honour and obey all that God doth ordain or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to be Rulers or governours over us.</p>
            <p>When natural men are lifted up high, and ſeem to obtain much credit in the world, then they may be lower, and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the waies of God then before, the God of this world having blinded their eyes, to keepe them hoodwinkt from the glorious light of the goſpel of peace, which offers peace to all.</p>
            <p>Behold I ſpeak not theſe things againſt you or your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, for <hi>I</hi> wiſh you all proſperity and health, and a ſetled peace in righteouſneſſe and true holineſs; but God hath ſent me to ſhew you your danger by plots, and which way to take to appeaſe his wrath.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The manner of</hi> Davids <hi>faln Tabernacle, how it fell, as well from the gentile Chriſtians, as the naturall Jews.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>My Lord, the means to bring us to a true ſetled and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed peace, is firſt to ſeek Gods kingdome, and the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs thereof, and all things elſe needful ſhall be added
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115635:6"/>thereunto; as when <hi>England</hi> formerly did flouriſh, both in Church and State, and was preſerved more then any other Nation from plots, conſpiracies, inbred-enemies, and forraign foes, as namely, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> invaſion, the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der plot, and many more, which for brevity ſake muſt be omited.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, there was a time that we were in Covenant with God, the temporal ſtate or Magiſtrate was a wall to the Church and Miniſtry, yet the Church in that time was not without ſpots, or State without corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>The Church was never a pure Church, free from blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, ſince the Primitive, Apoſtolical, and Diſcipled flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing time;
<note place="margin">Job. 38.7.</note> when the morning Stars ſang together un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the light, glory, and peace, which was obtained by the mercy and love of God in Chriſt, that immaculate Lamb, and his twelve Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">Meaning the Church was but one body ſerving God with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</note> which were to be Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers or Judges of the twelve ſpiritual tribes of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> then as <hi>Jacob</hi> and his twelve ſons were the firſt chief natural heads, ſo Chriſt and his twelve Apoſtles were the laſt chief ſpiritual Fathers or Brethren that laid the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation under Chriſt, to bring all nations under the Goſpel-Covenants, the which as many as believe and are obedient to, they are <hi>Abrahams</hi> Sons by faith, and Citizens of the new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> whoſe builder and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is God.</p>
               <p>The old <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> then flouriſhed, when <hi>Davids</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Son <hi>Soloman</hi> was King over the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he had built the Temple and dedicated it to the Lord by prayer, and religious feaſting, he was in Covenant with God. Thoſe were peaceable, plentiful and golden days for Church and ſtate.</p>
               <p>The new <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> wil never be in her excellency of glorious beauty; til God hath joyned the two ſticks in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one, <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Iudah:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 37.16, 17, 18, 19.</note> I mean the natural ſeed and ſpiritual ſeed under the ſeamleſſe garment of one govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under <hi>Davids</hi> ſpiritual Son, the ſecond <hi>Solomon,</hi> then wil that time appear that Chriſt wil reſtore the Kingdom
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115635:7"/>of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be under one government, and one body for the Church and State, which never hath been ſince <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> parted in <hi>Rehoboams</hi> and <hi>Ieroboams</hi> time; for as <hi>Solomon</hi> and his Son <hi>Rehoboam</hi> were the onely chiefe Cauſe or inſtruments of their parting, one by Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and the other by ſlighting or deſpiſing the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the Ancient; and following the counſel of young men, who were puft up with pride and covetouſneſſe, like the men of our late days, and ſo cauſed the Kings government to be rent in pieces by Gods Prophet,
<note place="margin">1 Kings 11.30, 31, 32.</note> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the greateſt part of the Houſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> to revolt from the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> which are not reconciled to this day.</p>
               <p>Juſt in the ſame manner fared it with the Chriſtian Gentiles which Chriſt &amp; his twelve Apoſtles firſt planted in the true Apoſtolical Catholick order: in one body un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one head who had a ſeamleſſ garment of pure govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which in proceſs of time was in a flouriſhing condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in one body of ſpiritual government: in thoſe proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous days of peace &amp; true Religion, moſt men gave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wholly to build and beautifie Gods houſe, being charitable minded in hoſpitality and Chriſtian duty: in thoſe days men did ſhine by godly pious, converſation without flattery or diſſembling hypocriſie, ſhewing themſelves, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, Aples of Gold pictured with ſtuds of Silver.</p>
               <p>But while many ſlept in ſecurity, Satan ſowed tares, which for want of being weeded out of the Church in due time, cauſed corruption to creep in by degrees; and at laſt to break out into idolatry, ſtrife, and hereſie, then the Chriſtian vail of Religious duties was rent in twain, as Chriſt ſignified at his death: by the renting of the vail of the temple, it is to be underſtood of the renting and deſtruction of the Chriſtian Temples by deviſion, as wel as the Jewiſh ceremonial Law, of which for brevity ſake many proofs for confirmation muſt be omitted; but this I give you to underſtand that <hi>Davids</hi> Tabernacle was raiſed, as wel to the Chriſtians Goſpel covenant as to the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115635:7"/>Jewes and natural Iſraelites under the Law, and likewiſe ſo it fell: you may queſtion me, ſaying, how can you prove that. I anſwer, When the Catholike Church firſt paſſed by diviſions, and groſſe errors, into jars and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen wars, and to part from one real body which was planted to be over twelve ſpiritual Tribes under one head in Chriſts Church, <hi>Abraham</hi> being their Father by true Faith, they being all ſpiritual brethren in Chriſt; then began they to kil, plot, perſecute, and revile one againſt another, pretending for Religion, but contrary to Chriſts covenant, or the Apoſtles doctrine.</p>
               <p>And ſo to this day we continue reviling, and hating one another, and they calling us Hereticks that are Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and we calling them groſſe Idolatrous wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipers, yet neither of us without great errors, and ſo we continue reſting Chriſts Goſpel-truth in unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by making corrupt Laws, on purpoſe to perſecute and deſtroy one another by Satans malice, contrary to Chriſt and his Apoſtles rule, or the true Primitive Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches practice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſhort deſcription of the ruinating of the Proteſtant Religion in this Land.</head>
               <p>THe onely cauſe of the controverſies between King and Parliament, was firſt pretended to raiſe up the Proteſtants againſt the Papiſts: ſome of the Proteſtants which were ticed to begin theſe late wars, but contrary to Chriſts command and Goſpel-rule, or the Apoſtles doctrine, to erect Chriſts Church by unnatural bloody war, therefore God ſuffered the Spirit of diviſion to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe among themſelves, and to leave the Papiſts ſtanding, and like unnatural brethren they have ruinated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. I mean the Proteſtant Church and all her go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, and the High-Prieſt, and all that Apoſtolical, Diſcipled houſhold caſt out for their corruption, when it was grown to a ripe head, much like unto <hi>Ely,</hi> as a judgement from the Lord, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115635:8"/>
               <p>All this came to paſſe by being carried on by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a religious reformation, but God ſuffered the inſtruments of his wrath to pluck the Proteſtant Church government to pieces, when it was ſo old that it could ſtand no longer. The chief workmen that did begin it wear covetous and new fangled Teachers, whoſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath long time hanged on the deceiving hinges of ſtrange opinions.</p>
               <p>Theſe things have been ſo far from plucking the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> down, that they have given many great cauſes for it to ſtand firmer then it did before; and to cauſe many to cleave to their Church. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as ſhe now ſtandeth will fall, but that muſt be done by love and a ſpiritual war as followeth.</p>
               <p>And as the late ſeveral choſen Parliaments were Axes and Sawes to hew down and part a ſunder corrupted go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments. So God hath ordained and put your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe chief now in power to build up and joyne both for Church and State, all things in better order then they were before this many hundered years: therefore take the founders and builders of the firſt Jewiſh and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches for your example</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The way to raiſe up Davids fallen Tabernacle,
<note place="margin">
                        <p>If fire have burned hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and good food hath ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited mens bodies, for want of being carefully uſed: ſhall we never uſe fire or food more, for the former abuſe of them?</p>
                        <p>Truly, my Lord, it is a fit compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for theſe things.</p>
                     </note> as in the dayes of old,</hi> Amos 9.</head>
               <p>HAving now declared the renting and dividing of Chriſts ſeamleſſe garment, my task is now to ſhew your Highneſſe how to raiſe up the Churchs ruines, and build it up as in the days of old, therefore take the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Jewiſh and Chriſtian Churces for your exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p>Firſt my Lord, you muſt ſet up a Patriarchal, and Apoſtolical true reformed Epiſcopal order; twelve Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs under the Law, twelve Apoſtles under the Goſpel; the twelve Founders-, Biſhops and Rulers of the Church, under one Spiritual head Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115635:8"/>
               <p>As <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> are called the Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all the Faithful, ſo Chriſt in God is called the Father, the true Church, the Mother, called the City or new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that is to be ſent down from heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.10. which City or new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw to have twelve gates, and at the gates twelve Angels, that is, Biſhops, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. to the Angels of the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> that is, the Biſhops of the ſeven Churches, and the names written therein of the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whoſe glory God cauſed to ſhine like pretious ſtones, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.11, 12, 14.</p>
               <p>And the wall of the City had twelve foundations, and in them the names of the Lambs, twelve Apoſtles, which twelve Apoſtles were twelve Biſhops, as appears <hi>Acts</hi> 1.20. let another take his Biſhoprick, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.25. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.8. there was ſuch a neceſſity of twelve in chiefe, that Chriſts Miniſtry could not be carried on af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Iudas</hi> his fall without that number, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.25. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63.11, 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> in a typical way, ſignifies God the Father, <hi>Iſaac</hi> is the figure of Chriſt, <hi>Rebeccah</hi> is the eſpouſed Church of Chriſt, <hi>Iacob</hi> is a repreſentation of the Holy Ghoſt, the which holy Ghoſt, or <hi>Iacob</hi> muſt beget twelve Patriarchs or twelve Apoſtles, which were the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Biſhops and Fathers under God in Chriſt, of the old <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> Iewiſh and Chriſtian, and muſt be of the new <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> which is to come.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe, when <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> was about to enter <hi>Canaan</hi> the Lord cauſed him to chuſe twelve men out of every ſeveral Tribe a man to bear twelve ſtones before the Ark, thorough <hi>Iordan,</hi> and to take them where the Prieſts feet ſtood firm, which ſtones they were to ſet up for 12 pillars in <hi>Gilgal;</hi> and he ſet up twelve more in the midſt of <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan</hi> in the place where the Prieſts feet ſtood that bare the Ark of Gods covenant, <hi>Ioſhua</hi> 4. which 12 pillars being ſet up in natural <hi>Canaan</hi> for a memorial of the dividing of <hi>Iordan;</hi> and being carried on the ſhoulders of 12 ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral men, out of every Tribe a man under the Law, as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115635:9"/>ſoon as they came to enter natural <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Signifieth the twelve chief pillars of Chriſts Church, which are to be the head Founders of the new <hi>Ieruſalem, Rev.</hi> 21.14. which muſt and will be ſet up when we are at the entrance of a ſpiritual <hi>Canaans</hi> peace. All Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are written for our inſtruction, and they ſpeak of things paſt, onely to tell us what ſhould be done now as figures and types of things to come.</p>
               <p>But happily it may be objected againſt what I have ſaid, that there were 13 Patriarchs and 13 Apoſtles: 'Tis true <hi>Iacob</hi> and his 12 ſons were 13, and a little before his death he received <hi>Ioſephs</hi> ſons by laying on of hands, to be as his ſons in his and <hi>Ioſephs</hi> place, to make for his 12 Tribes, 13 heads, fathers; of which <hi>Iudah</hi> was chiefe, in that he brought forth Chriſt. So likewiſe Chriſt firſt choſe 12 to be head ſpiritual fathers of the 12 ſpiritual Tribes, to make them one body under him the head, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>After Chriſts death, reſurrection, and aſcenſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the holy Ghoſt was come downe to give them the fulneſſe of their power and gifts, the number was made 12.
<note place="margin">Acts 1.</note> after <hi>Judas</hi> fall: but after the holy Ghoſt was come down to carry them on in their work, when they began to be perſecuted and ſcattered, it pleaſed God to convert <hi>Paul,</hi> even their greateſt perſecutor and furiouſeſt enemy, and to make them 13 Apoſtles, <hi>Peter</hi> being the head in Chriſts Church, and by his command to feed his Lambs and ſheep thrice; to whom Chriſt committed the keys of <hi>Davids</hi> Tabernacle, or heaven, to bind or looſe things either in heaven or earth, he being head the body were 12. Beſides, here in <hi>England,</hi> following that example at one time, as Chronicles ſhew, there were 24 Biſhops under two high Prieſts or Archbiſhops.</p>
               <p>Your Highneſſe muſt likewiſe remember that beſides this Apoſtolical order, you muſt ſet up a Diſcipled order of 70. both which Orders I ſhal prove firſt under the law, ſecondly under the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Your Highneſſe ought to remember the Law which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115635:9"/>gave to <hi>Moſes,</hi> to inſtruct you what to do, to be as it were a School Maſter, who when he found the government for Church affairs too heavy for him, he grieving and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his complaint to God the Lord, to eaſe him of his burden; God commanded him in <hi>Numb.</hi> 11. v. 16. to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeventy men of the Elders of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to bring them unto the Tabernacle of the Congregation to make a body under him and <hi>Aaron</hi> the High Prieſt, to be hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of Church government, which as ſoon as they were elected &amp; ſet round about the Tabernacle, the Lord took the ſpirit from <hi>Moſes</hi> and gave it to the ſeventy Elders, and they did all propheſie, and did not ceaſe, <hi>Num.</hi> 11.25. Thus you ſee God ordained the ſeventy Elders, even the compleat number when they were in the wilderneſſe, that were of <hi>Iacobs</hi> houſhold when they went into <hi>Egypt</hi> to make a body, above the ordinary Prieſts for Church af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, he wanted not Judges or Officers for State af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, or Marſhal diſcipline; he took his Father in Law <hi>Iethro's</hi> counſel for that, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>Secondly under the Goſpel, Chriſt our Saviour the onely begotten Son of his Father, when the fulneſſe of time was come, which God long before had determined, when he ſaid, <hi>The ſeed of the Woman ſhould break the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head,</hi> which is to be underſtood Jeſus Chriſt ſhould be born of a pure Virgin, which ſhould be ſet up as an Enſigne for the people and Nations, to lead the chiefe Officers of his Army in his life time, he gave no other weapons to the head Leaders and general Governours of his Army to carry on their warfare againſt all his enemies but the ſharp ſword of the ſpirit which proceedeth out of his mouth, to ſlay the enemies of him and his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect.</p>
               <p>Chriſt firſt choſe twelve, <hi>Mark</hi> 3. and he named ſome of them <hi>Bonerges,</hi> by interpretation ſons of thunder, then Chriſt ordained ſeventy other, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.1, 2, 3. and ſent them out when the harveſt was ripe, two and two toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into every City or place which way ſoever he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe would come, and he gave them power to carry on
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115635:10"/>their work: ſending them forth as Lambs among Wolves, and the ſeventy returned again with joy; ſaying, Lord, even the Devils are ſubdued to us thorow thy name: and Jeſus ſaid unto them, that he ſaw Satan like light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fall down from heaven: behold, ſaith Chriſt, I give unto you power to tread on Serpents and Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all the powers of the enemy, nothing ſhal hurt you; nevertheleſſe in this rejoyce not, but rather rejoyce that your names are written in heaven; the ſame hour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced Jeſus in the ſpirit, and ſaid, <hi>I confeſs unto thee, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Lord of heaven and earth, that thou haſt hidden theſe things from the wiſe and learned, and haſt revealed them to Fabes, even ſo father, becauſe it pleaſeth thee, Luk.</hi> 10.17, 18, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Truely my Lord, we muſt all believe that theſe very Scriptures are written for our inſtruction; there is none that believeth that God is God, and his Word is Truth, that dare object or ſay; but that theſe Scriptures are ſent from God to us for no other end, but to direct us to do the ſame, which they ſpeak of, that hath been done here to fore in former ages, for they are patterns, examples and lines for us in this laſt age, to erect, build up, and walk by, and although God hath hidden theſe things from the wiſe and learned of this time as it pleaſed him ſo to doe in former ages, as Chriſt ſaith <hi>Luke</hi> 10.21. and to reveale it to mean men, which are but like babes and ſucklings, yet let none that bears the name of a Chriſtian diſdain, neglect, or deſpiſe theſe things for the meanes of the perſon of him whom God ſpeaks this now but let all that will own the name of Chriſtians rejoyce, in the ſpirit as Chriſt their head Captain did in the ſpirit, giving all praiſe and glory to him, aſſuring themſelves that the meaner perſons, they are that God doth it by, the greater work of God is ſhewed therein, and with all expedition to ſet about the work, for by this example were our Primitive Chriſtians to chuſe their ſeventy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters. For when it pleaſed God to have the holy Scriptures tranſlated, or interpreted for the good of all that believe, he did it by ſuch a number of ſeventy, which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115635:10"/>were all guided by the holy Ghoſt, as it had been one man, and they were as it were conduit pipes to convey the water of life into all Countries, Nations, &amp; Tongue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, for the comfort of Gods Elect through out the World. Thus you ſee there is no contradiction with God, he is at the beginning and ending all one in his Church; for as God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are all one in Trinity, ſo is the true Apoſtolical and Diſcipled Church whom Chriſt promiſed the holy Ghoſt ſhould be with to the end of the world, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.16. <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.21. And every member of the body have their proper gifts for offices and places for the building up, ruling and gathering of the Saints under Chriſt their head, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12, As <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, God hath ordained in the Church ſeveral Officers; as firſt, Apoſtles: ſecondly, Prophets: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Teachers; then they that do miracles: after, the gifts of healing, helpers of governments, diverſity of tongues; but, ſaith he, are all Apoſtles? are all Prophets? are all Teachers? are all doers of Miracles? have all gifts of Healing? doe all ſpeak with Tongues? doe all interpret? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28, 29, 30.</p>
               <p>Theſe Scriptures ſheweth us very plainly,
<note place="margin">Proved that none of the new Elect, or Gathered Churches are not true Churches.</note> that all our new elect and gathered Churches are out of the ways of God at this very time, as far, I may ſay, as the Eaſt is from the Weſt; yet I wil not judge any: But there may be many true members that belong unto Chriſt among them; but thus by the power of God I wil aſſure you, that none of the new Sects as cal themſelves Churches, are true Churches, becauſe they have neither true heads or body above them, according to other Law or Goſpel rule, but every one ſtrives to be a Teacher, by reſting the Scriptures to their own corrupt finiſter by-paths, and ſo loſe themſelves, and lead many more into woods, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſes, and deſarts of ſtrange opinions; and ſo it wil be worſe and worſe ſtil daily, more every day then other,
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.11, 12, 13.</note> til the mercy of God cauſe us to have an Apoſtolical and Diſcipled body under a head for the gathering of the Saints together for the work of the Miniſtery, and for the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115635:11"/>dification of the body of Chriſt, this wil be the way to make all the members of Chriſts Church meet in the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of true faith, as followeth if you can believe.</p>
               <p>That the ſeventy Elders that God cauſed <hi>Moſes</hi> to chuſe had ſeveral prophetical gifts when they were choſen and brought to Gods Tabernacle, at that immediate time.</p>
               <p>Or if your Highneſſe can believe that Chriſts Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Diſciples had ſeveral prophetical gifts for the making of a compleat body for Chriſts Church: and the ſeventy interpreters of the Scriptures were guided by the holy Ghoſt: Then I intreat you for the Lords ſake who hath ſent me as a Herald to you, to cauſe you to chuſe ſuch a number as you ſee Law and Goſpel rule holdeth out a juſt proofe for; which being choſen, and elected as by the power of Gods holy word and ſpirit guiding me to direct you as, hereafter followeth.</p>
               <p>To ſhew your Highneſſe and all the world by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, which he is able to perfect, and make good in my weakneſſe. For as we read, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. that <hi>Elias</hi> will come before the latter day, to turne the hearts of Fathers and Children one toward another; and to end contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies in Families, Nations, and Kingdoms, leſt he ſhould ſmite the whole earth with curſing; that as where ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, warre, deviſion, and hereſies have moſt and laſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded, there grace, love, peace, and concord may firſt begin to abound, here for a true exampled pattern for all other Nations to follow us: for Chriſt ſaith the firſt ſhall be laſt, and the laſt ſhal be firſt.</p>
               <p>There is no fearful or doubtful queſtion, to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt this earth, and way which here is laid down the ground from antiquity of other ages, how God hath ſent the holy Ghoſt into ſuch an equal riſing number heretofore to carry on his work by; but that he will do the like now if we would deny our own corrupt ways, and embrace his waies, which are all grace, vertue and humility; for God is Alpha and Omega, at the beginning and ending of his workes, all one and the ſame, and his wayes of mercy are paſt finding out.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115635:11"/>
               <p>The Apoſtles ſay, that theſe days would not come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe there were firſt a departure of the Faith, by many falling into groſſe erronious hereſies, blaſphemies and apoſtaſies, there were never more then now: therefore we may well aſſure our ſelves by natural reaſon, that this is the very laſt age of the world, and ſhould be the beſt: but nature is more abuſed now then ever it was in our forefathers days; ſo that this time ſhewed forth it ſelfe to be the worſt, and the very dregs of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ages, that ever have been.</p>
               <p>For, behold, both natural pride, and ſpiritual pride, abound in every high degree; natural drunkenneſſe and ſpiritual, not onely by exceſſe of drinking, which is a very great reigning ſin in this land, but alſo Sects and ſelfe opinions, which makes many thouſands ſtagger without drinking of either wine or ſtrong drink, ſo that they are drunken and bereaved of all true ſpiritual ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; and many others are blind by ignorance, their knowledge being ſo weak and ſhallow in points of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that they know not their right hand from their left; and although they have been brought up as it were in the Schooles of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, by going to Church, hearing Sermons, and reading, or hearing the Scriptures, yet they are prophane and covetous, both people and Prieſts like one another, ſo that it grieveth the holy Spirit of our God to ſee his people deſtroyed for want of knowledge.</p>
               <p>In the late Biſhops time in ſome places we were gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a ſort of Shepherds,
<note place="margin">Of the late Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops time.</note> which although they were knowing enough for learning, and charitable enough to the poor in temporals, yet they were prophane by ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their flocks.</p>
               <p>But now we are troubled in moſt places, with a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous ſort of Teachers, I had like to ſaid in all places be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ignorant themſelves; they do not onely ſtarve their flocks for want of ſaving and ſound knowledge, but alſo for lucre ſake, they drive and carry them into by and ſeparate paths of errors and hereſies, ſo being like peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115635:12"/>like Prieſts, God hath puniſhed our ſins together, and yet our putrified ſins being not healed, are like to break out into another red ſea of blood, if God prevent not.</p>
               <p>Now the Church being thus brought into the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe weeping in her widows-like mournful Condition, as one that hath loſt her husband,
<note place="margin">Luke 10. Rev. 9.</note> and the Elders being all caſt out of the City, ſo that ſhe hath no guide for her children which are left alone among fiery ſerpent-like Teachers, and Scorpions and beaſtly poyſoned opinions, and the Ark and Temple of God is razed and taken by the uncircumciſed of heart; and we are a murmuring rebellious people, worſe then the Iſraelites were, for our God hath brought us thorow a red ſea of civil Wars, to an entrance of a ſpiritual <hi>Canaans</hi> peace.</p>
               <p>And if our rebellion againſt God doe not prolong our miſery, I fully believe we are neer the very entrance of a glorious time for the Church to break forth into her brightneſſe, and to ſhine in a more glorious manner then ever ſhe did ſince <hi>Adams</hi> fal: For the time is near at hand when all oppreſſors and diſſembling hypocrites which do not ſpeedily leave their evil ways ſhal be rooted out of power. And thoſe that have ſerved God, following the good old way, ſhal ſhine as the ſtars do in the firmament, both in Church and State, and to enjoy a true, religious, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>tled peace according to righteouſneſſe and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo that the civil Magiſtrate may be a wal to the Church and Miniſtery. Four Monarchs being broken down, there wil be another ſet up, even a Kingly pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er under the Scepter of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Believe not thoſe Dreamers, Mockers, Makers of Sects whoſe ſtudy is all to write or ſpeak great ſwelling words againſt dignities, and the powers which are ordained of God, nay even againſt the Lords day or Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and the ſacred ordinances of Gods Law and Chriſts command, even the ten Commands which God writ with his own finger in ſtone, never to be waſhed out or aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, having a double memento for the keeping of the Sabbath and Lords day, as wel to the Chriſtian Gentiles
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115635:12"/>as the Jews, for take away the Lords day, even the day which is ſet apart onely for his worſhip: if the candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick be removed away from us, the light of Gods true worſhip wil immediately follow, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. But as Chriſt ſaith, he ſaw Satan fal as lightning from heaven, and transforming himſelfe into a glorious Angel of light, to carry on many with their new lights and falſe viſions and new fangled doctrine, to deceive if it were poſſible the very Elect, but that is an impoſſible thing.</p>
               <p>More I would have ſpoken of the Chriſtian Sabbath, and of theſe ſtrange opinions, to ſhew every poor ſoule the ſubtile wiles of Satan, and the means at large how to eſcape him, in this time of ſpiritual blindneſſe and proud knowledge, which darkens mens mindes, and divides their judgements, by groſſe thick darkneſſe which if we have not loſt our ſpiritual feeling, we might feele it at none time, under the Goſpels glorious light; which makes many other doat away their pretious time:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Firſt a ſign of the Stars.</head>
               <p>ALL which wickedneſſe and Apoſtaſies are but ſigns of a glorious time at hand, nay even at our very doores. For as when the Stars are under thick miſts or clouds, that night is very dark, and the darkeſt part of all that night is immediately before the break of day; even ſo when the Churches Stars, the Miniſters are clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the foggy miſts and errors of factious Teachers which are clouds without water, as <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks. Even then is the Church in her dark mournful condition; which darkneſſe will appear moſt of all when the day of her deliverance draweth neer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Secondly, of the Moon.</head>
               <p>AND as when the Moon is neer her change, the night imediately before is the darkeſt night of all that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115635:13"/>quarter, ſo the ſad dark mournful condition of our Moon, the Church, gives us hope that ſhe is neer her change, and that the Son of righteouſneſſe is ready to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe with healing under his wings, and that the morning tide is neer a turning; the day of a true religious peace is neer a dawning, and ready to break forth into a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous light; thus you ſee the Churches greateſt extremities is always Gods chiefeſt opportunities.</p>
               <p>All which darkneſſe, confuſions and miſchiefs have ariſen for want of theſe aforeſaid apoſtolical and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled orders. For as Natures reaſon hath told you, that your Army could not ſtand without general field Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, above Captains of Companies, according to Marſhal diſcipline: even ſo ordinary Miniſters of pariſhes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand without Heads: as Biſhops, Deanes, and other Church-Officers according to Scripture diſcipline.</p>
               <p>If fire have burned houſes, and good dyet hath furfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted many mens bodies for want of being carefull and moderately uſed; ſhal we therefore never uſe fire or food more? Truely my Lord, this is a fit compariſon concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning theſe things.</p>
               <p>There is now a beginning of a fifth Monarchy or Kingly power;
<note place="margin">The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the fifth Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy.</note> Your Highneſſe is the firſt man God hath raiſed to be the man to erect it, and to be a Protector of the people in State, and to take the like care for the Church as <hi>David</hi> did for building up of the true worſhip of God, and as <hi>Davids</hi> deſire was to be a door-keeper in Gods houſe, after he had deſtroyed the Churches enemies in the time of the Law. So God hath appointed you to keep the doore to let none but the true Miniſters of Chriſt proved by Law and Goſpel rule, to enter into that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly office which have their calling and election from God and man and approved, able in gifts and ſound knowledge fitting for the diſpenſation of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of God.</p>
               <p>Your Highneſſe ought to take the firſt <hi>Solomons</hi> deſire of God, as an example to frame your heart, and to keep you from the deſire of riches, honour, or the life of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115635:13"/>your enemies; but onely beg of God for an enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of heart, for the guiding of ſuch a people as is committed to your charge, and then all other things that God ſeeth is needful for you, will be added with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out weariſome care, as both Peace, Safety, Plenty, and Wiſedome.</p>
               <p>And to haſten ſpeedily to ſet forward the finding out the true way for Gods worſhip to beautifie his houſe. Now you ſee God hath given you more power and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to doe ſuch a work then ever any King had ſince <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> firſt was a Kingdome; although you cannot chuſe but heare and know how many curſe you as <hi>Shimei</hi> did <hi>David,</hi> yet you ought to think as <hi>David</hi> did when <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mei</hi> curſed him: <hi>Surely this curſing and plotting againſt me is ſuffered by Gods ordination or permiſſion,</hi> becauſe ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you doe not ſet about the great Work of God, and follow Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Solomon</hi> by patience and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, praying for your greateſt enemies, and willingly and readily open a door of peace and truth to your grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt enemies that you have fought againſt; if you can perſwade your ſelfe the battels were for God, then the execution of vengeance ſhould be left to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The way to chuſe a High Prieſt.</head>
               <p>YOur Highneſſe ought firſt to chuſe a good Pilot or High Prieſt for the Church; a good, learned, ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Divine, ſuch a one who hath alwayes heretofore given himſelfe to charity and hoſpitality, apt to teach, a man of ſound judgment and grave knowledge.</p>
               <p>O for the Lords ſake, and for the good of the Church and people, and your own ſafety in this life, and for your ſoules ſafety hereafter, imitate <hi>Abrahams</hi> chief Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and eldeſt Servant; for God calls you to come to him, and to take a hallowed oath, as <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſervant did, being charged by his Maſter not to take a wife of a ſtrange linage, of the Canaanitiſh ſeed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom he dwelt, but to goe to <hi>Aram,</hi> to fetch
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115635:14"/>one out of <hi>Nahor,</hi> his own ancient Family.</p>
               <p>Even the like charge lieth upon you from your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Maſter, for to chuſe a Bride for his Sons Church of the Ancient, True, Chriſtian Religion, even a man of ſelfe-denial, that will leave all like <hi>Rebeccha, Geneſ.</hi> 24.</p>
               <p>Such a one to be a High Prieſt God the Father will take delight in: He that will aſſoone as he is called to Chriſts work, and that he is ſent for to be the onely chiefe Head under Chriſt in his Church, and to be his chief eſpouſed, as <hi>Rebeccha</hi> was to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> who as ſoone as ſhe ſaw <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the Field at eventide, alighted off her Camel and went on foot to meet <hi>Iſaac</hi> her Bridegroom, which went outto meditate in the field toward evening, who meeting <hi>Rebeccha,</hi> he brought her into his Mother <hi>Sarahs</hi> Tent after ſhe was dead.</p>
               <p>Even ſo will it be with us; though the old Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church be in a dead condition, yet let us aſſure our ſelves that Chriſt is neer a coming to meet the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of his Saints. Now it is eventide with them; yet mans extremity is Gods opportunity, for Chriſt will meet ſuch a one as is humble and lowly minded &amp; meek, and he will bring him to be a High Prieſt after <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dechs</hi> Order, in the Proteſtants place or Tent: And God will chuſe an Apoſtolical and diſcipled number to be added to him, they being choſen and ſet apart for that end by him. Even ſuch as will be willing to doe as <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus</hi> did, who when he was climbed up in a Syccamore tree to ſee Chriſt, as ſoone as he was called by Chriſt to come down, for he would that day dine in his houſe with him, yea rather in his heart, and told him further, <hi>That ſalvation was come into his houſe both for himſelfe and his Family.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So now the whole Land is ſoule-ſick to ſee moſt men, which are climbed up ſo high, and all in a pretending way at the firſt to ſee Chriſt, but nothing intending any ſuch matter, but to make themſelves great in the world, and ſo ſet themſelves againſt God and his glorious Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115635:14"/>which calls them to come down, as Chriſt did <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus,</hi> to be charitable to the poor, and reſtore to every one their right, and then Chriſt will dine in their hearts, and the holy ſpirit of union will caſt out the ſpirit of diviſion, and bring ſalvation to their ſeveral Families, and joyn them together in one united minde, with one accord to carry on the great weighty affaires both for Church and State, to begin the work in a perfect way, and ſo goe on to more perfection:</p>
               <p>Your Highneſs cannot chuſe but ſee what great things the Lord hath done for you, by preſerving your perſon in many and ſundry great Battels of war, and ſince, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeveral dangerous plots which have been lately found out, which for brevities ſake I muſt omit to name; all which plots and dangers ſhew you God is angry with you to ſee his houſe lie waſte ſtill, and no one is ſetting about the work of God.</p>
               <p>You may well aſſure your ſelfe that God is ſorely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed, that many are planting and ſetling themſelves in great Eſtates, and making themſelves great by this ſlaughterous wars, and ſo caſt Gods work behind their backs. Now his Houſe and Worſhip hath been pluckt down and brought to ruine by ſeveral Sects and evil members, which have ſome of them been of the Army, and the reſt the Army have favoured, I meane all Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, ſeditious and blaſphemous perſons, in this fiery time of trial, or conſuming of the true worſhip and zeal of Gods good old wayes of worſhip, which did ſhine in a flouriſhing condition.</p>
               <p>And now you ſee God hath preſerved your Highneſſe, as he ſpake by the Prophet <hi>Zechariah</hi> 3.2. concerning <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> the High Prieſt: <hi>The Lord will rebuke Satan, and chuſe Ieruſalem to reprove him.</hi> But ſaith the Lord, <hi>Is not this a brand pluckt out of the fire?</hi> And thus you ſee the Lord many times brings his beloved children very neare the very gates of Hell, or in great danger of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
               <p>And now you may ſee God hath pluckt your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115635:15"/>from among thoſe brands, and brought you to the Kings Throne, to be chiefe Ruler over all, as <hi>Abrahams</hi> eldeſt ſervant was. The firſt thing you ought to have done, that would have been moſt pleaſing to God, and beſt and ſureſt for your ſelfe, was to have found out the true worſhip of God, and to have been as faithful in chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a ſpiritual Head for the Church, the woman, as St. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw to be cloathed with the Sun, and the Moon under her feet, having a crown of 12. Stars on her head, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.1. being meant Chriſt, or one in his ſtead, twelve Apoſtolical governours called a crown of twelve Stars: that is, Biſhops of his Church, being cloathed with the Son of Gods bright garment of pure government: Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Moon under her feet; that is, all changeable governments which change like the Moon.</p>
               <p>Take one imitation of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſervant, who refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the eating of bread to feed his hungry appetite after his long journey, till he had ſhewed his faithfulneſs, and knew <hi>Rebeccha</hi> and her friends mind, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. So take heed of feeding your ſelves with worldly dignitie, till you have found out a Head, and an eſpouſed company to make a body for Chriſts Church.</p>
               <p>Take your example from <hi>Moſes,</hi> who after he was Gods chiefe ſervant, although he was brought up in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court by <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter, when he came to yeares of underſtanding, <hi>he refuſed to be called the ſon of</hi> Pharaohs <hi>daughter:</hi> O therefore take heed of thoſe Courtly offers after you underſtand the wayes of God, as either to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud or detaine any man from his Right, or keep the Church and people of God either in bondage or a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe condition.</p>
               <p>O therefore for the Lords ſake delay no more time, by building your own houſes, but ſet about the houſe of the Lord, which is called a houſe of prayer for all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p>For the neglect of that, God ſhewed you a ſign of his anger, when you were in that great danger of being kild in <hi>Hide Park</hi> on S. <hi>Michaels</hi> day, if you can beleive the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115635:15"/>word of God to be true, That God commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to put off his natural ſhooes when God called him from being a natural ſhepherd to be the chiefe Leader of his people, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.5. and likewiſe the ſame he command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Joſhua.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joſh. 5.</note> The ſhooes ſignifie the natural affection of a mans heart and minde, when he is called to the holy work of the Lord. We read that for a very ſmall offence the Lord met <hi>Moſes,</hi> and would have killed him in the way, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.24.</p>
               <p>And as the Angel of the Lord ſtood with his ſword drawn before <hi>Ioſhua</hi> to cauſe him to unlooſe the natural ſhooes from his feet; if the Lord hide it not from you, and ſo leave you off to hardneſſe of heart and ſpiritual blindneſs, you may well ſee that the Lord is not pleaſed, by the many dangers you have been near. All thoſe plots and dangers ſhould be as warning pieces to ſet you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to goe about the work of the Lord, or as goads to ſtir you up to it. I intreat the Lord, and oftentimes doe pray that God will be pleaſed to open the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al eyes of your ſoul, and clear up your underſtanding, that you may goe about the great work of the Lord with all expedition.</p>
               <p>And you may well aſſure your ſelfe, that if the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den was too heavy for <hi>Moſes,</hi> who had his counſel at Gods own mouth, who had likewiſe <hi>Aaron</hi> the High Prieſt, and other Prieſts to aſſiſt him; yet it made him to cry out to be eaſed of the Lord, or ſlain. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the example of the Jewiſh and Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches lead you as a pattern or line. Chuſe firſt a High Prieſt, then 12. and gather 70.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115635:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The manner of the High Prieſts receiving the number of</hi> 12. <hi>for to be Apoſtolical Biſhops, by the holy order of laying on of Hands, and then</hi> 70. <hi>proved from</hi> Jacob, Moſes, <hi>and the Apoſtles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>octrine.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOur Highneſſe having according to Gods command and Scripture rule to be your guide, choſen a High Prieſt for the head of Chriſts Church, as <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> were; and then by the High Prieſts advice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ordaine twelve Apoſtolical Biſhops, as ſeveral heads under him, for to be over the twelve ſpiritual Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> or Chriſts Church; the High Prieſt ſhould not receive them to be his ſpiritual Sons without the laying on of hands: this holy order and confirmation of laying on of hands I ſhal prove to you by example from <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 48.14. who when he was about to die, and to receive <hi>Manaſse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Ephraim</hi> into the number of his twelve Sons, to make them thirteen Head Fathers of the twelve natural Tribes of <hi>Iſrael, Manaſſeh</hi> and <hi>Ephraim</hi> being called the two halfe Tribes; at <hi>Jacobs</hi> receiving of them at the hands of their Father <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to make them as his ſons to bear their part of his name for the time to come through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all generations; he did not do it without laying on of hands and, receiving them without that holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to confirm them by his bleſſing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> at his bringing them to old <hi>Iacob</hi> his Father, whoſe eyes were dim, his ful intention was, that old <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> ſhould have laid his right hand on the eldeſt, and his left on the youngeſt; but he would not do ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his natural eyes were dim, yet God gave him the ſpiritual eyes of the ſoul to diſcern that the youngeſt ſon ſhould come to be greater then his brother; although, ſaith <hi>Iacob,</hi> I know <hi>Manaſsch</hi> ſhal be great, yet his youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger brother ſhal be greater then he, for his ſeed ſhal be ful of Nations; and he ſet the youngers name before the elders. Although it much diſpleaſed <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> who ſought meanes to prevent his Father for doing thus; yet <hi>Iacob</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115635:16"/>knowing the decree of God, would not alter it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 48. from the tenth verſe to the end of the Chapter.</p>
               <p>A little before <hi>Iacobs</hi> death he called all his ſons toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bleſſe them, and to ſhew what would befal every one of them in the latter days: and how <hi>Iudab</hi> ſhould be the heads in that out of his linage Chriſt was to come, and all people ſhould be gathered to him.</p>
               <p>In theſe prophetical ſignes <hi>Iacob</hi> is a repreſentation of the holy Ghoſt, and likewiſe for the manner and number of his family.
<note place="margin">Of <hi>Moſes</hi> lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> he followed this example of <hi>Iacobs</hi> laying on of hands, Scriptures make no mention of it, but a little about the time of his death, <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.9. This Text of Scripture ſaith that <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Nun</hi> which was the ſucceeder of <hi>Moſes,</hi> was full of the ſpirit of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; for <hi>Moſes</hi> had put his hands upon him, and he and <hi>Iſrael</hi> did as the Lord had commanded <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Apoſtles and Diſciples time at the Goſpels firſt plantation, as it is written for our inſtruction in ſeveral places of the Acts of the Apoſtles, how that by their lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands many received the gift of the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Paul</hi> at one time laid his hands on twelve ſeveral men, and they all received the gift of the holy Ghoſt and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied: and furthermore <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth his ſon <hi>Timothy</hi> whom he had begotten. Saith he, <hi>Deſpiſe not the gifts that is in thee, which was given thee by propheſie, by the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands by the Presbytery Elders,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.14. All theſe Scriptures were written for our inſtruction and learning, there is none that believeth in God and his word that dare or wil object againſt it: thus you ſee here is proved in Chriſts Church an example of twelve Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Biſhops under a High Prieſt, otherwiſe called an Archbiſhop, and a Diſcipled number of ſeventy, to make a compleat body beſides, and the order of receiving of them in their ſeveral places and degrees into that holy office of the Miniſterial Function and body of Chriſts Church according to thoſe holy orders which have been alwayes practiſed by the ancient Fathers of both Jewiſh and Chriſtian Churches, in all former ages.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115635:17"/>
               <head>One Objection anſwered by Scripture ground and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But happily many in our days may be apt to raiſe Objections againſt this truth, that is ſo manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved here by Gods holy Writ, ſaying, that Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Elders are all one; therefore, ſay they, there need be no other order but a number of Elders according to the Presbytery, which order is mentioned in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. To anſwer theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bjections and make them fall to the ground. Look in the fifteenth Chapter of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and the firſt, ſecond, and third verſes; when there was a great diffention and diſputation about Circumciſion by <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> againſt them: at laſt they ordained that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> and certain others of them, ſhould go up to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> unto the Apoſtles and Elders of the Church. The word Apoſtles in all places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtandeth before the word Elders: <hi>Paul</hi> was one of the twelve Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.28, 29. Eph 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Barnabas, Stephen, Timothy,</hi> and the others in their ſeveral places were of the company of the Elders of the Church, <hi>Acts.</hi> 20.17. Multitudes of Texts and Scriptures might be raiſed to confirme this truth, to ſhew that there was firſt an Apoſtolical number as chiefe, twelve: and then Secondly, a diſcipled number of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty according to order then in thoſe dayes: and that order would have continued till this very time, had not corruptions and diviſions caſt them out of the Church.</p>
               <p>But this I can by the power of God aſſure your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and all others that deſire to know; that we ſhall never enjoy perfect peace nor true Religion till that time be, that there be ordained for the Church ſuch an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical and diſcipled number; the which being done by God and mans appointment, having their commiſſion ſigned and ſealed by God and man, and being entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a hallowed Covenant at the Ark or Tabernacle of Gods teſtimony, meant the Church, being received and ordained every one according to order to make a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat body: by joynt order their chiefe reverent father in God ought not to receive them into this holy office
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115635:17"/>without the laying on of hands: the which being done, and they joyned together as one man for the work of the Lord, for the ruling and gathering of the Saints, and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding up of true Religion, being thus elected and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeu.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The true way to prove them by going to ſpiritual war with all Sects which are the true Churches enemies.</head>
               <p>YOur Highneſſe and many more may queſtion me, or demand, ſaying, How ſhal wee know whether thy calling and election be of God, and ſure and firm, and not of mens traditions, or ſuperſtitious conſecrating?</p>
               <p>'Tis anſwered thus.</p>
               <p>It wil be known by this manner of trial that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, whether or not that they be the onely men God hath appointed to beautifie his Church, and to raiſe up <hi>Davids</hi> fallen Tabernacle here firſt in this land, and to be a pattern &amp; example for all other lands to follow them.</p>
               <p>Your Highneſſe and they muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lame open ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al war againſt all Sects that hold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Church fellowſhip, that call themſelves Religions: and they may be all comprehended under four heads, as namely theſe, 1. <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> 2. <hi>Independents.</hi> 3. The <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> muſt be calld. And laſt of all the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> that is in theſe dominions, muſt be call'd to this ſpiritual war, to bring them to the Touchſtone of Gods word.</p>
               <p>All theſe aforenamed Churches ſo called, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whatever, ought to have both leave and command from and by your Highneſs, to come to diſputation, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with them of the late and new ordained Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is the Apoſtolical and diſcipled Body under a ſpiritual Head: Then as <hi>Iude</hi> ſaith, there will bee earneſt contending among all theſe ſeveral elect for the faith once delivered to the Saints: every ſect, ſuch a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain number as equalizeth the fore named being choſen and ordained according as beſt pleaſeth their ſeveral judgements or opinions.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115635:18"/>
               <p>When this Herald or Trumpet is ſounded which God wil cauſe his holy Angels to ſtir up the hearts of men to do it in his good time, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.30. to gather his elect from the four winds, to ſee the true way to joyne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the true Miniſterial head and body of Chriſts Church, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. in one united faith.</p>
               <p>For when theſe ſeveral elections are gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there wil be caſting of lots among theſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſouldiers that are called to this ſpiritual war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare to ſee which can gaine Chriſts ſeamleſſe garment of government, which ſo oftentimes hath been parted and rent to pieces, and dipt in Chriſtians blood formerly.</p>
               <p>And there wil be likewiſe a caſting of rods alſo toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther one with another; the <hi>Egyptians</hi> rod that would keep the Church in bondage, or the covetous idolatrous time ſervers, or the divided new fangled people, or the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> All theſe their ſeveral rods may turne like Serpents, or bud many Scriptures each of them; But <hi>Aarons</hi> rod, or the true Prieſthoods iron rod wil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour up the reſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ods, and break their power to pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces like a potters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, all that are Antichriſtian, or Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical, or ſeducing.</p>
               <p>Yet they may at the firſt bud many Scripture phraſes, like the true Prieſthood in the fight of the ignorant, but they wil ſoon diſcover themſelves when they come to the touchſtone of trial, by diviſion to bring themſelves to confuſion, and ſo ſilence themſelves.</p>
               <p>But the true Prieſthood which hath his foundation from Antiquity, that is, entered into a hallowed Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God, and joyned together in a compleat body under a head, ſhal then ſhew forth themſelves to be the true Prophetical and Apoſtolical Diſcipled Church, in a moſt manifeſt way they wil then appear before al people by their ſeveral gifts and places; being all guided by the ſpirit of Union; for their rod wil not onely devour the other Serpent-like rods, but alſo it wil bloſſom, and the ſpirit of <hi>Daniel</hi> wil appear in their lot to defend the woman, Chriſts eſpouſed Church, which otherwiſe if ſhe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115635:18"/>were not known by this kinde of trial and ſpiritual war, they would judge her to be a Whore ſtil, and ſay ſhee were as full of fornication as other-idolatrous Churches have been in other Kings reigns before: But now ſhee wil prove her ſelfe to be a pure Virgin: and that day the iniquity of <hi>Jacob</hi> wil be removed out of this land, <hi>Zach.</hi> 3. and the Whore of <hi>Babel</hi> ſhal fal, and all falſe formes, ſhal ſink in the Sea like a Mil-ſtone, never to riſe again: then wil that Scripture be fulfilled, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.1. The Woman wil appear cloathed with the Sun, and the Moon under her feet, and that's meant all changable Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſhe wil have a Crown of twelve Stars on her head; which is to be underſtood the new <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> Church, cloathed with Chriſts righteouſneſſe, and the twelve Stars are the twelve Patriarchs, or Apoſtolical Rulers, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.11, 12, 13, 14. And Chriſts promiſe then wil be fulfilled to his twelve Apoſtles, when he was with them on the Earth, that they ſhould be head in chief o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and the fulneſſe of the Gentiles brought in, and the Jewes called, then the kingdom wil be at this immediate time reſtored again to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and all the kingdoms of the earth wil be under the glorious government of Jeſus Chriſt; and the foure beaſts, and the four and twenty Elders wil caſt downe their Crowns before the Lamb that ſitteth on the throne praiſing God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>By the four Beaſts we may underſtand the four Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies, or head ruling powers that have been already broken to pieces, and brought to their former beginnings of nothing againe, when their corruptions were growne ripe.</p>
               <p>By the 24. Elders are to be underſtood 12. natural Patriarchal Judges under the Law for Temporals, under a natural Head, a King; and 12. Apoſtolical Spiritual Biſhops over the Church, under their ſpiritual Father, the Head of the Church, the Judges of late years have turned judgment for the poore widow and fatherleſſe into wormwood and gall, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.3, 4, 7. <hi>Amos</hi> 6.12.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115635:19"/>
               <p>Though the temporal Father of the State be now cut off and caſt out for the corruption and bribing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality of the Judges, and the Judges held in at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but not without great corruption; and God hath ſo ſeverely dealt with the ſpiritual Father, and all his Houſhold, to cut off the Head, and caſt out the body; but look what <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17. <hi>But the time is come that judgment muſt begin at the houſe of God: If it firſt begin at us, what ſhall be the end of them that obey not the Goſpel of God? Wherefore let them that ſuffer now accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will of God, commit their ſoules unto him in all well doing as unto a faithful Creator.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Look what <hi>Ieremiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chap.</hi> 23. <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4. Though it hath befel ſo with our Church of late yeares, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God hath ſuffered his people to be thus ſcattered, <hi>Yet they ſhall be brought again to their folds, and he will ſet up Shepherds over them, which ſhall feed them, and they ſhall dread no more nor be afraid, neither ſhall any of them be lacking, ſaith the Lord. Behold, ſaith the Lord, the dayes ſhal come that I wil raiſe unto</hi> David <hi>a righteous branch, and a King ſhal reign and proſper, and execute judgement and juſtice in the earth,</hi> Jer. 23.5. And <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. That God wil reſtore to us Shepherds for the Church, and an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical diſcipled order above them under a High Prieſt.</p>
               <p>Even ſo his promiſe is to reſtore to us a true ſtock of Judges under a temporal Head, their true borne King? In his dayes Judah ſhal bee ſaved, and Iſrael ſhal dwel ſafely. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.9. <hi>In thoſe dayes, ſurely ſaith the Lord, I wil turne to the people a pure language, that they may call upon the name of the Lord, and ſerve him with one conſent. And all powers wil be broken to pieces, and the Heathen ſhal be ſmitten by that ſharp ſword which proceedeth out of the mouth of God. And he</hi> (according to his promiſe) <hi>will rule the Heathen with an iron rod; for he it is that treadeth the winepreſſe of the fierconeſſe of the wrath of God,</hi> Pſal. 2.9. Rev. 2.27. Rev. 19.15. Then wil that time be that the ſwords ſhal be broken into plow-ſhares, and the ſpears in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115635:19"/>pruning-hooks, and Nations ſhal have no more cauſe to lift themſelves up one againſt another in warlike man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I intreat your Highneſſe, and your wiſeſt Counſel, for the Lords ſake, that you wil make no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, but ſpeedily with all expedition chuſe ſuch a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber by election and holy ordination, that is, laid down a perfect rule from the Scriptures, and a command from God, and try them by ſpiritual war againſt all Sects and ſelf-opinions, and they wil bring the Church out of her wilderneſſe and widowhood-condition, not onely of all danger of being brought into danger again, but alſo through theſe red ſeas of bloody wars which have been maintaned under the pretence of Religion, but contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Chriſts command or Goſpel-rule. Likewiſe they wil cauſe theſe feigned Rivers of <hi>Iordan</hi> to be dried up, that all the Iſrael of God may come unto one united ſpiritual <hi>Canaans</hi> peace, within the Harbour or Suburbs of the new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to make us all Citizens of that place which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw in his Viſion to have twelve gates, and at the gates twelve Angels with the names written on them of the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the Lamb, and his twelve Apoſtles, which are the chiefe Founders and Builders of this glorious ſituated govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Wee muſt underſtand, that as the judgments of God firſt began at his own houſe in this Land; ſo God wil have his houſe reſtored and built up again, to be as it were a pattern for the King and Lord Protector to frame and ſet up their State-government by. For a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there is to be appointed by God twelve Apoſtolical Biſhops un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Head ſpiritual Father, to be the Leaders of the Church ſo far as their power can wel be able to rule; ſo likewiſe it is convenient to have 12. temporal Judges in chief, under one Father, the King, ſo far as their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is wel able to extend in every diviſion; which being thus done according to order, righteouſneſſe, and true holineſſe, every Kingdome wil then become the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115635:20"/>of our Lord and of his Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15, 16, 17.</p>
               <p>So then the King being as <hi>Abraham</hi> or <hi>Moſes,</hi> in chief under God the Father,
<note place="margin">Exod. 4.16.</note> he muſt be as <hi>Moſes</hi> was to <hi>Aaron,</hi> as it were a God to the High Prieſt, or Arch-Biſhop. The High Prieſt or Arch-Biſhop repreſenting <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Rebec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> by a <hi>Melchiſedech</hi>-order of Chriſt, muſt be as it were a chiefe Prophet to the King, as <hi>Aaron</hi> was to <hi>Moſes:</hi> And the twelve chief temporal Judges, and the twelve Head ſpiritual Biſhops, which make the number of 24. El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, muſt caſt themſelves down, with all their govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both for Church and State, to give all praiſes to God the Father and his Son Chriſt Jeſus, for judgment given to the great Whore; and the other 70. diſcipled El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders wil doe their office as God wil appoint them to, and carry them on by the power of the Holy Ghoſt. And the High Prieſt ſhal then weare no more polluted garments, but God wil cauſe him to have change of ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a fair Diadem or a Micre on his head as <hi>Aaron</hi> had.</p>
               <p>And then the Church wil begin to flouriſh in a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manner,
<note place="margin">This fifth and laſt elect 70. wil by Gods aſſiſtance beautifie the fifth Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy.</note> and God wil carry on this laſt 70. under the High Prieſt and the 12. Apoſtolical Biſhops, which are to be heads of the 12. ſpiritual Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Gods holy ſpirit guiding theſe, and going along with them, they wil build up the truth Church better and firmer then ever it was before, advancing the true worſhip of God above all. Zach. 3.</p>
               <p>And they wil give example for the Judges and State-officers to follow them in like manner; for the ſpirit of <hi>Daniel</hi> wil be among them, ſtanding in the Lot: the dark letters and the hidden myſteries which are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to man, God by theſe wil unſeal, and God wil eſteem of them as his deareſt Jewels.</p>
               <p>Theſe wil be guided by the Holy Ghoſt to doe as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> exhorteth, to purge the tin and the droſſe from the go Iden and filver governments.</p>
               <p>The two famous Univerſities and Schooles of learning
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115635:20"/>ſhal be made pure fountains by theſe, from whence the ſincere milk of Gods word ſhal flow for the nouriſhment both of Church and State, to feed the flock and people of God as the breaſts of <hi>Sarah</hi> and <hi>Rebecca</hi> did nouriſh <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then ſhal all houſes of hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality and religious ſtore houſes be ſetled &amp; eſtabliſhed according as is intended to their right end again, the ſtore houſes to be rightly erected without either I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry or Superſtition, for an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Tithes and other things to be brought in thither, that their may be proviſion for Gods houſe, for all neceſſary u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that belong thereunto, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word of God, that being their guide; and all pariſh Churches, and Places that are or have been appointed for Gods worſhip, as neede requireth to be deſently reſtored to their Prieſtine adornments, to make them the beauty of holineſſe, as Gods word requireth, without ſuperſtition or idolatry, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order,</hi> and the Miniſtery for every de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree rightly to be reſtored, and they to have their charge and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from the Apoſtolical Biſhop and Diſcipled Elders of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral limitted Dioceſſes in all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees as belong to the Miniſterial office to be as careful of their chargeover every Pariſh according to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115635:21"/>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> ſoundneſſe of Doctrine and integrity of life, and to be as careful over all ſorts of people that belong to their congregated charge, in all need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful degrees, as great rich mens Shepherds muſt be over their folded or paſtured Sheep, which were onely kept and appointed for that end, if any of their flock be loſt by the Shepherds negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, as earthly Maſters wil look for the price of the ſheep at their hand as is hired and kept for that end.</p>
               <ab type="comments">Zeph. 3.9. <hi>Saith the Lord, ſurely I will turne to the people a pure Language, that they may call upon the name of the Lord, and ſerve him with one conſent.</hi>
               </ab>
               <ab type="comments">Lord haſten this time.</ab>
               <ab type="comments">In this time of the kingdom of glorious grace, there ſhall no man need to ask the wayes of God of Lay men, but we ſhal all be taught of God, and fed with the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere milk of Gods word, which floweth from the mouth of Gods meſſengers, the true Miniſters. Every neighbour and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man to follow his temporal calling, living in unity, ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an brotherly love; ſaying one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, where ſin and envy hath heretofore
abounded, ſo now true love &amp; grace ſhal much more abound, ſerving God with one conſent, ſaying one to another, <hi>Come let us go up to the houſe of the God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>to learn of his true Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds and Miniſters,</hi> We may wel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude &amp; believe this to be the time that the whole earth wil be filled with the knowledge and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Lord, as the waters covereth the Sea.</ab>
               <ab type="comments">Yea much more muſt the Miniſter, Shepherd, or Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man give an account both to God and them, as God hath ſet over them of their charge, for if any be loſt for want of their care, their blood God wil require at their hands, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.</ab>
               <p>The ſame charge lieth upon me or any other that hath a meſſage to declare from God to your Highneſſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſeeing of a ſword or a judgement, or an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of the times; we muſt not fear to declare the mind of God, for the diſpleaſure of either King or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate; if we doe, whenſoever it be, they die in their ſins or ignorance for want of having warning by the ſeer, that God revealeth it to; they ſhal die. and their blood ſhal be required at his hand.</p>
               <p>For by this which I am to declare to your Highneſſe, I am appointed of God to aſſure you, and the whole Council of State, that although other powers of the late ſeveral choices for Church and State have not ſought
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115635:21"/>Gods ways but their own; yet thoſe that God wil per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect his work by, he wil have them to deny all to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt: although the other ſelfeſeeking powers took not <hi>Solomons</hi> counſel, who exhorted them to take away the evil counſel from before the King, and the Kings Throne ſhould be eſtabliſhed according to righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, but they wilfully and unadviſedly took away the King inſtead of his evil Counſel to eſtabliſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by it in great places; theſe natural warriers did it unadviſedly by ſpiritual blindneſſe, yet the thing could not be omitted becauſe it was long before ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined of God.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſpiritual warriers will reſtore his ſon again to the royal Throne, to be ſupream, in more Dignity and Majeſty then ever his Father enjoyed it, to be eſtabliſhed in and by peace, if God harden not the Churches ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to their own deſtruction, as he did <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his hoſt; nevertheleſſe whatever the malice of Satan and wrath of wicked men do endeavor themſelves againſt the ways of God: yet it wil be at laſt for their greater ruine that withſtand the wil of God: the more violently they withſtand it, the more God wil be glorified by their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, which wil come upon them like a ſuddain whirlewind, when God ariſeth to deliver his Church: Fhr God and his choſen as he will doe his work by, he wil cauſe them to reſtore every thing in the right or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, both in Church and State, which hath been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed and disjoynted this many hundred yeares; and ſo he wil preſerve it til the end of all things come to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution; becauſe God hath the hearts of all Kingly Potentates in his hand, to diſpoſe of them as pleaſeth him, either for the eſtabliſhment of a Nation in peace, or the remove of them by war.</p>
               <p>I muſt needs be bold to ſpeak and declare my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the preſence of God, and the like to all the world:</p>
               <p>Concerning King <hi>Charles</hi> his Life and Death, that for ought I could ever ſee or heare upon ground or proofe,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115635:22"/>waving afide envious or ſlanderous aſperſions caſt upon him, that are now plainly ſeen were caſt upon him, to carry the deſign of his enemies on againſt him in a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent way, as things were laid to <hi>Davids</hi> charge that he never knew of: If Chriſt were ſo wronged by falſe witneſſe, and put to to death, and his Apoſtles, Martyrs and Saints, and the holy men of God in all ages, let no man judge the worſe of him for his untimely death; for there is a righteous Judge that knoweth all, therefore let every man begin to judge his own heart, and there he ſhal find himſelf to be in a great high rebellion againſt God, and guilty of high Treaſon. The meaneſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as God made for our neceſſity and ſervile ſervice, in their nature doth condemn us in the things they were created, for ſo they remain ſtil.</p>
               <p>I cal God to record, I ſpeak nothing in his behalfe, no not a word more then I would for any man elſe, for God cauſed me to fortel his overthrow, and I have had great loſſe and trouble by ſome that were of his Army; yet I have been long aſſured, and cauſed to write and ſpeak how that he was the Lords anointed King, and that his conſcience being firm to maintain the ancient Rights of the Proteſtant Church, was the cauſe of his death. Furthermore I am forced to foretel how that his Poſterity and Heire wil come to enjoy the Crown: And this I am cauſed and compelled to ſpeak, as I have heretofore foretold by the power of God, of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt remarkable changes and chances as have fel out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween King and Parliament, neer this 12. yeares paſt, which is all come to paſſe ſince but onely the manner of Church-government, and the Kings Son being reſtored to his Fathers Throne, and in what manner, if any man wil needs ask me what ground I have for it, I muſt needs tel him, it is the witneſſe of Jeſus, which is the ſpirit of Propheſie, which hath carried me on in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Not that I can fortel any of theſe things by any power of my own, or by any natural Art; but when it pleaſes God to compel me, then I cannot forbeare to goe.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115635:22"/>
               <p>As for King <hi>Charles</hi> his life, they could ſpeak no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of him when he reigned in peace, but that he was a loving godly peaceable Prince, ſticking cloſe to the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental point of the Proteſtant Religion.</p>
               <p>I butſaid many he was almoſt turned Papiſt; but they that caſt that aſperſion upon him firſt, ſoone after, when they had made many beleeve that, then they ſaid the Common-prayer and the Proteſtant Religion was all I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous Popery, and ſo they eſteemed Charity a while after. I judge noue that were the inſtruments of the Kings death, I with great fervency of ſpirit pray that his bloed may not cry to Heaven for vengeance like <hi>Abels,</hi> but like our Saviours; for they that were the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, did not know what they did, God hiding it from their eyes by their ſpiritual blindneſſe, as the Jews that put Chriſt their heavenly King to death.</p>
               <p>I fully believe that this City of <hi>London</hi> wil be a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ordained by God to reigne over the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> I ſpeak not this by any prophetical com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, but by permiſſion and ſeveral natural rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as cauſe me ſo to think.</p>
               <p>You know <hi>Paul</hi> was a great man in diſcernment of the wayes of God by Viſions, yet he ſpake many things by permiſſion more then onely Gods immediate command at all times to him; but this by the power of God, and his holy ſpirit that I hope dwelleth in me, and I truſt wil alwayes guide me in all my wayes by his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the way of truth, both in ſpeaking, writing, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and talking, I wil ſhew you.</p>
               <p>As our Saviour Chriſt was envyed by the Phariſees, and put to death by their Counſels, but not againſt the ordination of God, by thoſe hard hearted Jewes; yet Chriſt prayed for them, and his death was a deſtruction to their Religion, even of thoſe wilful blinded Jewes, that put their King Chriſt to death by the Souldiers who guarded them to doe it.</p>
               <p>Even ſo wil it prove in the end with thoſe Phariſalcal <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> that firſt put to death their High Prieſt,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115635:23"/>raiſed up ſome of the Army, which cauſed the King to be put to death; alſo they gave the firſt onſet by their preaching and covetous lives, to raiſe Sectaries and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifies to be the inſtruments to doe it, it could not be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, it was both permitted and long ſo before deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined that he ſhould be cut off by an Army and a flood of-Hereſies, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.3, 4, 7.</p>
               <p>The King he imitated Chriſt and <hi>Steven,</hi> in praying for his enemies, and to be a meek man and a godly Chriſtian Prince, ſtanding firm for the Proteſtant Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
               <p>But by the Biſhops death, which none but the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Prieſts were the cauſe of, that every one of them thinking to reign as Biſhops by it, ſome of them gave the firſt onſet to ſet others againſt the King: But the death of the King and the Arch-biſhop, which all Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries thought to have reigned in a living condition by it, and knew they could notwithout it; yet his death and the Biſhops wil prove to be the death of al Sects and Herefies, and the chiefeſt meanes under God to convert the Jewes, Pagans and Turks to Chriſts truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:115635:23"/>
               <head>The Lord guide me with this holy Spirit</head>
               <p>I Shal aſſure you in truth, eleven year agoe, I being an Apprentice to an Iron-Monger, it happened by the powerful providence of God, as I was at a Fare on the longeſt day of the year, called Saint <hi>Barnabies day,</hi> as I was helping my Maſter to keep the Fare at <hi>Newport-pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel</hi> in <hi>Buckinghamſhire,</hi> I being in perfect health, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily exerciſed about my Maſters imploiments with him at the ſtall.</p>
               <p>About 12. of the clock as I was weighing out of ware, and many people at the ſtal, I was ſtruck of a ſuddain with amazement; the power of God cauſed me to look before me, and there was ſtanding before me the ſhape of a Woman, cloathed in blew, like an old faſhioned cloak and ſafeguard,</p>
               <ab type="comments">The Woman cloathed in blew raiment ſignified the Proteſtant Church. <hi>Aaron</hi> the High Prieſt his colours were blew for the Ephod, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.28, 31, 37.</ab>
               <p>the likneſſe of her face was black as an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</p>
               <ab type="comments">Her blackneſſe of face ſignified that ſhe began then to be overwhelmed with darkneſſe, lamentations, &amp; miſts of Hereſies, as <hi>Jude</hi> calls them, <hi>Clouds without water.</hi>
               </ab>
               <p>ſhe ſtrook her hands over her face.</p>
               <ab type="comments">Her ſtriking of her hands over her face in a mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful condition, ſignified the lamentable condition which ſhe then was fallen into, when the High Prieſt and the Apoſtolical, and Diſcipled Elders were caſt out of the City, and there
was no true government then, either in Church or State, when Kingly power was ſpurned againſt, and ſo fearfully deſpiſed &amp; weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſo that the Judges and civil Magiſtrates could not be a wal to the true Orthodox Miniſtry, then many old hereſies which had been long ago buried began to be new digd up, new fangled opinions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be found out by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans malicious temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</ab>
               <p> I took as little notice of it as I could, but was following my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters occaſion of trading, being a waighing of nailes I was ſtruck fick at heart of a ſuddain, and was forced to look on the ſtrong appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſſion
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115635:24"/>which was like a Woman, and looked ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly on her, who ſtrook her hands again over her face in a wailing condition as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>man that had loſt her h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> and, or children, or ſome great friend, and ſo ſhe vaniſhed away.</p>
               <p>I was very heart and ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach ſick, of a ſuddain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forced to leave the ſtal I told my Maſter I was not wel, I went to his Inne, and being very ſick, I vomitted blood: after a little time being ſomething better, I went to my Maſter againe, and ſtaid by him all day, but not without much paine, this was on the Satterday, and was I ſick and heavy at heart, and all parts of my body many days after, but I praiſe God I ſlept very wel every night, but could not tel what ailed me, my ſtomach was gone, I could not eat any thing at all, nor drink any thing; but what was ſoure like vinegar.</p>
               <p>I told my Maſter at night of the ſtrange appariſſion and viſion, and of my ſickneſſe, but he believed me not, ſo we went that night to <hi>Eubourne</hi> in <hi>Bedfordſhire;</hi> on Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day I was not able to goe on foot, but rod on my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters hackney horſe moſt of the way to <hi>Hampſteed</hi> in <hi>Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire.</hi> On Teuſday we went to <hi>Watford</hi> fifteen miles off <hi>London,</hi> but very ſick and weak I was every day, yet ſlept wel every night. On Monday we returned home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; I riding with much pain on horſeback, I beſought the Lord with a fervent mind, to be merciful to me, he heard my prayers, and as we were riding about a mile and an halfe off <hi>Redburne;</hi> the Lord made my heart to think, and my tongue to ſpeak, and tel my Maſter, that if he would goe by <hi>Redburn,</hi> it being neer a mile out of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115635:24"/>his way, <hi>I</hi> might ride home in a Waggon; he asked me how I could tel, or with whom; I told him with my Father; for I told him my Father had two Waggons then in <hi>Redburn,</hi> it being at mid time of the day; and how that my Father was there and one Brother, and his man. I had no natural reaſon to ſay ſo, for I could not tel they were in thoſe Countries, but onely the Lord had revealed it to me, who reveales his ſecrets to them that fear him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25. &amp; 34 his holy Angels pitch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s their tents about them.</p>
               <p>My Maſter was unwilling to go that way, but with much intreating did, and we found them in <hi>Redburn</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the Lord had cauſed me to ſpeak. My Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter overwent me that day, and left me to ride in my Fathers Waggon.</p>
               <p>On Thurſday night, we came to <hi>Toſſeter,</hi> fifty miles from <hi>London, Coventrie</hi> rode; my Fathers Inne was at the <hi>Saraſens</hi> head; but my Maſter appointed if I was not able to ride home, I ſhould be carried to his Inne, which was the fign of the Peele.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as <hi>I</hi> came thither, I defired to goe to bed, preſently with in an hour after, my Fathers Brother and many more came to ſee me, and asked me how <hi>I</hi> did, <hi>I</hi> told them <hi>I</hi> praiſed God <hi>I</hi> was better then <hi>I</hi> was before, and many ſuch words.</p>
               <p>I told them of the ſtrange Viſion in the Fair at <hi>Newport-pannel,</hi> but they beleeved me not, and the manner of it oftentimes; and how the Lords Revelation to me made me know where to meet them, which was againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures reaſon: My brother offered me to watch with me all night; no ſaid I, brother goe to your bed, and take your reſt, for I praiſe God I am better then I have beene ever ſince I ſaw the Viſion. So they left me.</p>
               <p>There was no Gueſts in the houſe that night, and <hi>I</hi> did lodge in an upper roome, a good diſtance from the people in the houſe; and I had been hot and cold on a ſudden, my cloaths being light and thin on my bed, and I was dangerous ſick, neer unto death of a ſudden,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115635:25"/>not thinking I could poſſibly live while morning: it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the dead time of the night, I could get none to come to me by knocking or calling. The Lord put it into my mind of a ſudden that I ſhould live to ſee an end of theſe troubleſome times, and how God had ordained me to be an inſtrument to the bringing it to paſſe: Lord ſaid I to my ſelfe, how can can this be, ſeeing I am thus weak, not like to live til morning? My heart began to ſink, ſo that I could ſcarce ſpeak. Within a little ſpace the Lord ſtrengthened me wonderfully, and put it into my heart to hang my cloaths about me, and goe out of my bed to other beds in the next chamber, and fetch cloaths: I being not able to ſtand, crept on my hands and knees, and fetcht the cloaths of two other beds, and with the help of Gods holy Angel laid them on my bed, and went to bed again.</p>
               <p>A while after, being ſomething warm in my bed, the Lords Angel gave me warning that I muſt undergoe the ſtrongeſt temptation that night as any man had endured; yet the Lord would uphold me in it. Dear friends, it was no dream nor fancy; for I was awake, and had my perfect memory.</p>
               <p>A little while after there was as it had been a book o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in my conſcience, I cannot forget the remembrance of the letters ſtil; and there was laid to my open view and memory all the ſins that ever I had offended God ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by omiſſion or commiſſion; and the Lord aſſured my conſcience they were forgiven aſſuring me that they were buried in the Sea of Chriſts blood.</p>
               <p>That was no ſooner paſt, and another Book opened, but there came into my mind a remembrance of al my deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing between man and man, and there was found no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation againſt me, but onely for 4 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr> which had been neer ſix years paſt. For the firſt journey that ever my Maſter ſent me out with iron ware, he ſent me three dayes journey from his houſe to a place called <hi>Cheſsom</hi> in <hi>Buckinghamſhire,</hi> and before I came home againe, <hi>I</hi> loſt 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> of my account, and having caſt it up at <hi>Warwick,</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:115635:25"/>the laſt night of my journey, and then I fearing to tel my Maſter of it, kept halfe a peck of oats from my hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, thinking to get the ſhilling that way at ſeveral times; ſo after with my with my Maſter, <hi>I</hi> loſing 8 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr> and wronging the dumb creatures of their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, my conſcience being troubled at it, did ſo no more.</p>
               <p>And when <hi>I</hi> was at the point of death, God ſuffered two ugly Devils, in ſhape like Blackmoors to accuſe me before him; ſo that <hi>I</hi> was forced to look out of the bed, and they ſtood between my bed and the window at my left hand: <hi>I</hi> was in a terrible fright, they ſtanding neer my bed-ſide a little after midnight. The Lord gave me a ſtrong ſpirit to reſiſt the Fiends by prayer, which made them fly from my bed-ſide. And Gods holy Angel com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted me exceedingly, and ſo left me for a little time.</p>
               <p>Anon after there appeared another Devil, who was transformed into a glorious ſhape, whoſe adornments ſhone like gold, as it had been a great Emperor, King, or Monarch, with a Crown on his head, who would have perſwaded me to have denied that Chriſtian Faith as <hi>I</hi> was trained up in, and renounce the Baptiſm as <hi>I</hi> had received in my infancy, and <hi>I</hi> ſhould bee in as great eſtimation for the time to come as any in the world.</p>
               <p>I endeavoured to pray againſt thoſe perſwading temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, but my own heart would have deceived me one time, <hi>I</hi> could ſcarce keep my mind cloſe to God; and being mighty hot by ſweating, and faint by ſickneſſe, my ſoule deſired to keep cloſe to God. My heart was brought very weak, <hi>I</hi> was brought ſo feeble-minded, <hi>I</hi> thinking all hope paſt but <hi>I</hi> muſt yield; at laſt <hi>I</hi> ſaid, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void Satan.</p>
               <p>At theſe words, and many more ſuch like, the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Fiend vaniſhed away; and the Angel appeared at my right hand as <hi>I</hi> lay in my bed, and ſtrengthened me with exceeding inward comfort, and ſo left me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:115635:26"/>
               <p>The black Fiends appeared a ſecond time, and being reſiſted by prayer, they fled. And there was another like a General, or great Commander, in gay apparel, in ſeveral colours, as red, black, green, yellow, in a bunch, perſwading me as the former did; but the Lords power was ſtrong in me to reſiſt him by prayer, which made them fly from my bed-ſide; then began it to be a little morning-light. <hi>I</hi> prayed all night, looking every mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute when the Lord would fetch away my ſoule from my body, but <hi>I</hi> deſired much of the Lord to live to ſee my Father and brothers, and to make a Will to diſpoſe of ſome little money, and ſome cattel; ſome to the poor, ſome to my brothers, ſome to friends, according to my Talent as <hi>I</hi> had.</p>
               <p>When the day began to dawn in my chamber, there was the ſhape of a Ladder, reared from the chamber-floor to the window; the top of the Ladder was above the window, the two ugly black Fiends and the transform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Devil appeared again neer my bed-ſide in violent way to feare and tempt me. <hi>I</hi> prayed to God for defence and ſuccour; the transformed Devil, ſhining like an Angel of Light, ran up to the top of the Ladder above the window, there <hi>I</hi> was tempted again; the two black Fiends ran up after, and ſtood one above another on the Ladder, calling to me twice, and ſaying, Come, wil you come? The Lord ſtrengthened my heart to prayer; the transformed Fiend vaniſhed away from the top of the Ladder: The ugly black Fiends, after they had turned feet to feet, the ones head was up towards the top of the Ladder, the others hung downward, and thus they hung their ſoles of their feet together on the Ladder. I thought all this while on <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder. Lord, thought <hi>I</hi> to my ſelfe, this is ſuch a Ladder as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaw in his Viſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.12:</p>
               <p>At the end of theſe terrible fights of the fearful Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I brake forth, uttering theſe very words, ſaying, O my Saviour, thou that waſt tempted and hadſt no ſinne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> able to ſuccour me a poor finful creatore; in the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115635:26"/>name of the whole Godhead avoid Satan. The one fel one way, the other another way, the Fiends parting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder; and <hi>I</hi> praiſe God <hi>I</hi> had no more temptation all the reſt of the time of my ſickneſs.</p>
               <p>And the Angel of the Lord came and comforted me, and told me when <hi>I</hi> was reſtored to health <hi>I</hi> muſt go on Gods meſſage to the King, and tel him he muſt agree with the Parliament, and condiſcend to them by agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and forgive them that which had been paſt, as a loving Father, although it were againſt him in that way as he was in and his Army: if he did refuſe to doe it ſpeedily, and for to work Reformation both in Church and State, if this were neglected, the Kings Army would come to nothing but deſtruction, and hee would be deſtroyed and cut off, but yet his Son would come at laſt to reign.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>I</hi> was to tel the Parliament, in withſtanding the King they muſt not doe it to make themſelves great, but perform their vow, for the ſetting up of Gods truth in the true purity for Church-government; and for Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and State Affaires, it muſt be to maintaine true Judgment in all degrees for the Magiſtrate according to truth.</p>
               <p>If this in the beginning were not their ayme, and in the end in the end their actions, God would blaſt all their proceedings, by one power diſplacing and diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving another, til at laſt their hereſie and injuſtice and diviſion would bring them to confuſion.</p>
               <p>And the Angel then gave me direction how the King and Parliament muſt make their agreement at laſt, and what form and manner the Church muſt and would be eſtabliſhed and governed. And how that God had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained tha <hi>I</hi> muſt be one of the three, and my Talent was to ſhew firſt the Church-government.</p>
               <p>And after, in my fickneſſe the Angel revealed to mee againe, how that all Countries would riſe in a triumph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing manner, with all ſorts of Muſick, and ſo come up to <hi>London</hi> with great joy, to eſtabliſh the King, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115635:27"/>all the enemies of Chriſt and his Goſpel, and caſt them out of power, and then all ſword-powers would begin here to ceaſe, and as a pattern other Nations ſhould follow.</p>
               <p>I ſhould have ſpoken of the manner of the ſickneſſe, and more of Gods great goodneſſe to me; but for brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-ſake I end with praiſes to God</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The reaſon why God ſuffered the two two black Fiends to accuſe me for the groat as I wronged my Maſters horſes of their allowance, gave me warning after for ever wronging my fellow ſervants more, if it ſhould lie in my power after.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As much it ſignified and breatned to any that either are, have been paſt, or ſhal be for time to come, put in power above men, to be Rulers either in Church or State, if they wrong, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud or ſmite with the fiſts of iniquity,</hi> Matth. 24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They that doe ſo, without repentance to God, and reſtorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to man, like</hi> Zacheus, <hi>God and their own conſcience will finde them out, and Satan wil bring bils of indictment in this life or after: For we have all one Maſte- in Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Satans transforming himſelfe into a glorious ſhape, and perſwading me to renounce my infant-baptiſm, and the feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed apparition of</hi> Jacobs <hi>Ladder, ſignified all Sects and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opinions, that are tempted by Satan to renounce their infant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſm, to go after the feigned River of</hi> Jordan, <hi>perſwading others to follow their ſteps up</hi> Jacobs <hi>Ladder, which is not the true way to Heaven: Therefore, as Chriſt ſaith, Neitherbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve nor follow them,</hi> Matth. 24.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>A ſhort deſcription of ſome of my great Troubles.</head>
               <p>AFter the firſt Apparitions, Revelations, Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Viſions that the Lord bad made knowne unto me his unworthy ſervant, many of his ſecret deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined intents which ſuddenly were to befal the King and Parliament both, Church and State, and a meanes how it might have been prevented, and a true peace ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, if they would but have denied their own corrupt wayes, to have imbraced Gods wayes.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115635:27"/>
               <p>And further, when the word of the Lord came firſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me by his holy Angel, to cauſe me to goe on Gods meſſage, firſt to the King, and then to the Parliament, to declare God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mind unto both parties, as <hi>I</hi> have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before, and what great troubles <hi>I</hi> muſt undergoe by croſſes, impriſonment, violence from my neareſt friends, loſſe of goods, if <hi>I</hi> refuſed to goe at firſt, to diſpleaſe them: yet after many troubles <hi>I</hi> muſt goe at laſt.</p>
               <p>When God had reſtored me to health and ſtrength of body again after my ſickneſſe, through my friends per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion <hi>I</hi> left Gods meſſage undone, and caſt his will behind my back; but many times <hi>I</hi> ſhould talk of it to many of my friends and others, telling them in what manner God had appeared to me, and what a charge was laid upon me from God to preſſe me on to diſcharge my conſcience, <hi>I</hi> oftentimes ſpeaking of it with griefe; but they moſt of them would be ſtil perſwading me that it was a temptation of Satan and his deluſions, and would bee arguing much with mee, that in theſe dayes God did not appeare by either apparitions, viſions, or revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſaying thoſe things were now ceaſed.</p>
               <p>Thus their perſwaſion wrought upon mee by Satans temptation to let Gods work alone for the ſpace of above three years. In this time <hi>I</hi> had ſome great troubles: The firſt of them was when <hi>I</hi> thought <hi>I</hi> ſhould have been mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to a Neighbours daughter as lived neere my Maſters dwelling, one of a good portion and parentage. Shee was my firſt love, being made ſure one to another by ſtrong promiſes in the way of contract between our ſelves: it was broke by falſe pretended friends, and ſo parted. <hi>I</hi> looked upon it no other way then this, <hi>I</hi> was aſſured that God did cauſe my proceedings in the world to be croſt, becauſe I had not been obedient to what <hi>I</hi> was commanded of Gods holy Angel, and confirmed by ſure ſignes.</p>
               <p>Within the compaſſe of a year after <hi>I</hi> was married to another rich mans daughter of my own trade, being ſet up to follow the calling of an Ironmonger at <hi>Hales Owen,</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115635:28"/>five miles from <hi>Brimingham,</hi> lived peaceably with my Wife, kept neer 60. Nailors at work to make iron ware. <hi>I</hi> kept great trading, and many horſes to ſend ware up unto other Countries, for to ſerve whole ſale to many Chapmen.</p>
               <p>In this time I had many troubles and loſſes, which if <hi>I</hi> ſhould lay them down in particular what I had before I was forced by God to goe on his meſſage, and thoſe as I have endured ſince, in the manner as they have befel me, and Gods mercy to me in delivering and preſerving me from one time to another, in no ordinary way, but in a miraculous way, the like was ſcarce ever heard of by any; if <hi>I</hi> ſhould put them in a Book, it would be lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then could be read in the lengeſt day in the year, and yet all true and good reading, to ſhew the wrongs as I have endured by my neereſt friends, and ſhe that was my Wife, with ſome of her friends, and many more, which before I went on Gods meſſage ſhewed great love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me; but when I went on purpoſe to the King, when Colonel <hi>Graves</hi> was his Keeper at <hi>Holmby,</hi> they were all great friends, but after, profeſt enemies againſt me by Satans malice, to wrong me in the higheſt degrees that ever was heard of by any man in ſuch nature ſince the world began, not onely once or twice, but ſeveral times in ſeveral yeares; yet <hi>I</hi> praiſe God I can ſpeak it with a good conſcience, in the ſight of God and man, that there is none of my greateſt enemies can ſay upon truth, neither wil they <hi>I</hi> believe, that I in all my troubles as I have undergone, I ever wronged man, woman or child willingly, not ſo much as to uſe any extremity againſt any of my greateſt enemies, but ſtil committing all to God, and praying for my greateſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, which are ſure fignes and ſtrong teſtimonies to all that know me, that <hi>I</hi> have been all this while guided, preſerved, and carried on by a miraculous providence of Gods holy ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Firſt, when I went to ſpeak with the King, Colonel <hi>Graves</hi> was his Keeper at <hi>Holmby:</hi> I being compelled by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115635:28"/>God to leave all and goe to foretel King <hi>Charles</hi> what would ſuddenly befal him if ſuch things were not done as the Lord had ſhewed me concerning his agreeing with the Parliament to erect and ſet up the true Religion of Jeſus Chriſt in the good old way, and that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy ſhould be as a wall to the true Miniſtry.</p>
               <p>I having theſe things in my breaſt to declare to the Kings own perſon by word of mouth, I comming very neer to the Kings Majeſty, being at bowles that day at <hi>Boulten Court,</hi> two miles from <hi>Northampton,</hi> with many Noblemen and Gentlemen to attend him, I was fearful and baſhful to be ſo bold as to ſpeak my ſelfe to ſuch a perſon as a King, I being ready to ſpeak ſeveral times, but being poſſeſt with ſlaviſh fear, I called Colonel <hi>Graves</hi> aſide, he being my neighbour-countryman, and of great acquaintance with his kindred and family, I told him what my occaſion was to ſpeak with his Majeſty, and what it did concerne, who walked a great while with me: I declaring Gods m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſage to him concerning the King and Parliament, hoping that he would have been an inſtrument to have brought me before the King, being it was ſo that the King was his priſoner, he told me he durſt not let me ſpeak to the King, for he feared I would ſpeak thoſe things to the King as would be diſpleaſing to ſome there, and ſo he ſhould be blamed, and I might be troubled becauſe notice was taken of my calling him aſide.</p>
               <p>He ſaid to me, Countryman, Countryman, trouble not your ſelfe with the theſe things, but goe home and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low your calling, for there are many which are crack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brain'd comming with ſuch ſtories to the Parliament, and I belieeve this is a temptation of Satans working upon you.</p>
               <p>Sir, ſaid I to Colonel <hi>Graves,</hi> you ſhal find it no ſuch matter; for if there be not this ſpeedy agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween King and Parliament upon theſe con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tions, that the Proteſtant Church may be truly and rightly reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo that the King, Judges, and Civil Magiſtracy may
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115635:29"/>be reformed according to righteouſneſſe and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that they may be as a defending wall to the true Orthodox Miniſtry, according to that direction as God declareth to you by me now, and more fully he would if you would beleeve what he ſpeaks now by me. The King wil be taken away in a pretence to doe him good; but many intend to deſtroy him.</p>
               <p>When I had declared Gods meſſage to Colonel <hi>Graves,</hi> I was eaſed of my burden. I went home thinking to follow my Trade again cloſe ſuddenly, not thinking theſe things ſhould be any hinderance at all to me. But God was angry with me, becauſe I having loſt ſuch an opportunity in ſpeaking to the King by ſlaviſh feare, but muſt needs declare it to him that prevented me.</p>
               <p>After they had taken away the King from <hi>Holmby, I</hi> went to ſpeak with General <hi>Fairfax</hi> concerning the King and Parliaments agreement, and Church-government, but was prevented.</p>
               <p>God ſuffered Satan to raiſe my Wife and moſt of her kindred to be violent againſt me, my Wife being there at that time, according to her and their deſire, ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great with child, neer her time of deliverance, after they had gotten a great part of my beſt goods and ſtock to their houſe, uſing much deſperate cruelty againſt me. The very remembrance of it grieves my heart to ſpeak or think of it ſtil. Before the time as God cauſed me to goe to the King, my Wife and I lived as peaceably as any man and his Wife did in our Country, and as much true love was ſhewed to her by me; but for her part, ſhe fel off to be my bittereſt enemy, for want of being guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the true love and fear of God.</p>
               <p>When they had forbid me to come to the houſe; yet patiently I endured, hoping to have overcome all my enemies by love, I came oftentimes to ſee my Wife, I was many times in great danger of being kild among them: Their Neighbours did lament my ſad conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and wil witneſs the ſame, I ſeeking no Law nor Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice againſt them.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:115635:29"/>
               <p>When the very time of my Wifes deliverance was come, ſhe forced me from her with bitter ſwearing and curſing, forbidding me ever comming neere her more, being ſet on by her Mother. So at that time I left her with a heavy heart, praying for her, and telling her that I would pray to the Lord earneſtly that he in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy would preſerve both ſhe and the child from death; but yet to cauſe her not to be releaſed of her tormenting paine, til ſhe was glad to ſend ſpeedily for me to be a comfort to her, and to confeſſe the wrong which they had done me.</p>
               <p>The Lord heard my humble prayers; for ſhe was neer three dayes in travail, and could not be delivered, til I was at laſt with all haſte ſent for. When I came to her, ſhe lovingly embraced me with bitter teares, laying great blame upon her Mother and the reſt of them that were my enemies, deſiring me ſpeedily to goe to prayer for her, and ſo I did, and ſhe was immediately deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of a daughter, and we were all friends againe; and ſhe was forced to confeſſe the great wrong they had done againſt me before many women that were their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
               <p>Her Father did ſeem to love me all this time, cauſed my Horſe to be put to graſſe, and deſired rue to ſtay all night. At evening his eldeſt ſon came home, and gave me very bad words, telling me he would turne my horſe out of the ground, and taking a riding rod in his hand to drive out my horſe, having laid a great club in a private place in a readineſs, intending to knock me down privately. I followed him, deſiring him not to ſhew himſelfe ſo uncivil againſt me as to put my horſe out: I having neither ſtaffe nor any other thing in my hand: I being before him when he came to the private place where the great club was hidden, he had like to have beaten my braines out of my head before I was aware of his wicked villany, being in the dark evening time, yet I ſaw a glimpſe of the blow coming toward my head, and ſtepping cloſe towards him, I put it by my head
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115635:30"/>with my arme; if Gods mercy had not preſerved me a thouſand to one <hi>I</hi> had been ſlaine, I dare ſay it was his bloudy intent, and many more, ſuch deſperate at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts I ſeveral times eſcaped.</p>
               <p>Thus they abuſed me, and ſold my horſes among them, and broke me of my Trade. I then began to ſeek out to the Juſtices for a warrant, being thus abuſed for my patience ſake; but before I could bring them before the Juſtice, they had cauſed me to be brought into great miſery, uſing my own money as an inſtrument. They wrought upon my Father by the worſt enemies I had, to perſwade him I was troubled with diſtraction; and becauſe my Father hearing I had been with the King at <hi>Holmby,</hi> and writing and talking ſtrange things, though it were of God, yet underſtood not, he conſented for to cauſe me to goe to be a while with a Doctor, rather then they ſhould ſhew violence to caſt me into priſon by falſe ſwearing; and to draw my Father to be willing to that, they made promiſes that a while after <hi>I</hi> ſhould have all my goods reſtored againe. They knew there could be no other mask to cover that vilany as they had lately done againſt me, but onely to cauſe many to think I was out of my wits, to make good their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</p>
               <p>But Brethren, it was ſo thought of Chriſt, when he began to put in practice his Fathers buſineſſe, when he choſe his twelve Apoſtles, <hi>Mark</hi> 3.17.21. and called ſome of them ſons of Thunder, his kindred thought he had been beſide himſelf, intending to lay hands on him: if it were ſo judged of Chriſt by natural men, let not his ſpiritual ſouldiers be aſhamed to be called mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and ſo all natural men doe all Gods people. But all that ever ſaw me, let them be enemies or friends, I praiſe God cannot but ſay I ever ſpake ſenſibly, with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, and very wel in the Scriptures, which made all that heard me admire to heare me ſpeak, and to read thoſe things which I wrote, having no natural learning
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115635:30"/>to attain to it, but the dictates of Gods holy ſpirit to preſs me on to it.</p>
               <p>And when all this miſery, and much more had befel me, I willingly ſubmitted my ſelfe under this great bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of afflictions, to Gods protection, and to be ruled by my Father counſel, although I knew it were againſt me. But when I came out of that miſery, I went to a Juſtice of the Peace againe for a warrant to bring ſome of the chiefe actors of my miſery before a Juſtice in <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſterſhire,</hi> on <hi>Midſomer</hi> day was ſeven yeares paſt; and when I had laid open the wrongs to him, it much grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him, and all that heard of it. The Juſtice promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me that I ſhould have juſtice, for he had heard that the whole countrey ſpake wel of me, and cryed out againſt them for wronging of me.</p>
               <p>So I went that day after to ſee my unnatural Wife, to her Fathers houſe, and finding none at home but ſhe with her little child, I was glad. She pretended a great deale of love to me when ſhe ſaw me, by outward ſignes of weeping, and good words, as ſhe ſate by my little child, it lying in a Cradle.</p>
               <p>My Wife deſired me not to think of any difference that had been paſt, but to forget is, and to goe as ſoone as poſſibly I could to houſe-keeping again, for ſhe told me that they began to lead her a very diſquiet life. Quoth I to her againe, <hi>I</hi> hope all wil make for the beſt, to cauſe your love to cleave to me againe; for ſaid <hi>I,</hi> you ought to forſake all your friends to live with your lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving husband, you know Gods word commands you ſo to doe.</p>
               <p>I deſired her never to ſo much as think any more of any thing that had been paſt, but now to turn over a new leafe, as though we had been newly married; and ſo ſhe made great promiſes to me that ſhe would.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> further asked her how it was poſſible we ſhould keep houſe ſo ſuddenly againe, ſeeing they had ſold my hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and broke me of my Trade? She told me her Father would reſtore to me ſuch things again, for he loved me
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115635:31"/>wel ſhe ſaid, and was ſorry for me.</p>
               <p>I took the little infant out of the cradle, and ſate me down on a ſtoole at the end of the cradle, and layed my ſtaffe at my feet, for I was fearful of more miſchiefe if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the reſt were at home, which made me doe ſo.</p>
               <p>My Wives Mother, and her daughter <hi>Katherine</hi> being neer the houſe, and ſeeing me when I came fromward the Juſtices, they laid a plot, thinking that I had been for a warrant for them, if they could perſwade my wife to take their part, they would fall upon me, and ſo would take their oath all three when they came before the Juſtice, that I offered them wrong, and ſo make their owne matter good, and throw me in priſon again.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as they came into the houſe, they called my Wife from me, and told her privately if ſhe did not help to aſſiſt them againſt me, they ſhould be utterly undone and diſcredited: So ſhe preſently yielded to her Mothers and middlemoſt Siſters counſel, and came preſently from them. I had the child on my knees, and was playing with it: She took up my ſtaffe as lay at my feet, and made as though ſhe would have carried out of the hall into the parlour; ſhe turned back againe ſuddenly with a great blow, and ſtruck me on the head and ſtudied me, and caught me by the throat, and pluckt me by the haire of the head, and beat my head againſt the wall; her Siſter being a great luſty wench, came running upon me too, and beat me about the head with my own ſtaffe; and thus I lay with the child on my knees, leaning with my back againſt the wall, my breath being almoſt gone: yet I praiſe God I lay quietly til the Lords providence had cauſed me to paſſe the child ſafe off my knees into the cradle without harme, I ſitting as the end of the cradle.</p>
               <p>I looked up, and ſaw my Mother in Law comming in upon me too. I by the power of God who preſerved me, and in abled me, gave my wife a puſh on the breſt as hard as J. could, and flung her backward. J. leapt up and pluckt the ſtaffe out of her Siſters hand, and gave her but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115635:31"/>one I bow, which lighted on her arm, and bruiſed it forely, that the ran away crying, and her Mother. My wife, as ſoon as ſhe could recover her ſelfe to get up, ran and took up an axe, and came having it up above her ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, with the edge towards me, ready to cleave my braines in twain: J ſtrook up my hand quick under the head of the axe by the handle, and put it by my head: all this being done, and J being wounded. My Wife with that one blow J gave her on one of her breaſts, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver gave ſuck more of that breaſt, which made me very ſorny: Her Siſters arme was ſo bruiſed, that it was lame above two years after.</p>
               <p>The Angel of God that preſerved me, cauſed them to be ſo wounded; for J dare ſweare J ſtruck but onely thoſe two blows; for J had ſo much patience from God that time, that J was not angry. Her Siſter and Mother ran both out of the houſe; J ſtayed my wife by the arm, and told her if ſhe had not betrayed me with her <hi>Judas</hi>-kiſſing and diſſembling weeping, J had not ſo much cared.</p>
               <p>J never ſtruck woman before that time, nor ſince, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would I have done it then but in defence of my life. A while after, ah <hi>Briget,</hi> ſaid J, when thou haſt done all againſt me as can be done, thou wilt be ſorry for it, and ſorely repent it: For J fully believe, ſaid J, that it is not thee, but the Devils temptation, and thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers bad counſel, for lack of ſerving God; but if thou wilt ſwear, ſaid J, that thou wilt not come neer them for a great while, and goe along with me from them, J wil freely forgive thee, and never ſpeak of it to any man. I ſpake thus, but not intending to doe it ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. She replyed againe, ſaying that ſhe would never live with me more curſing me in the name of God with many bitter curſes.</p>
               <p>Then I ſpake mildly again to her, ſaying, J pray you fetch ſome beere, and let us drink together before we part; J ſaid ſhe, if J could finde any Rats-bane to poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thee, J would. So I left her, and went to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115635:32"/>houſe, with a heavy heart the Lord knoweth.</p>
               <p>So the next time I went to the Conſtable, with a warrant to bring them, her Mother, eldeſt Brother <hi>John,</hi> and Siſter <hi>Katherine,</hi> before the Juſtice; but before I could have my warrant executed, they lighted on mee firſt, and her eldeſt brother that before had like to have kild me, having an Officer ready, arreſted me of flat fellony, I being kept as a felonious priſoner. So <hi>I</hi> ſent for my Father: when he came, my Father-in-Law and he took up the matter, and made agreement, with my Fathers perſwading me. <hi>I</hi> preſently imitating Chriſts forgiving his enemies, committed my cauſe to God, and was perſwaded by my Father and Father-in-Law. But <hi>I</hi> came not neere my wife a great while after, but abode with my own Father: And I began to follow my trade againe. My wife ſeeing that, ſhe made many friends to come to live with me again, making great moane, and ſhewing her ſelfe very penitent. <hi>I</hi> being perſwaded by my Father and many friends more, conſented; and we lived together again at a place called <hi>Harburn</hi> in <hi>Stafford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> two miles from <hi>Brimingham.</hi> My loſſe was above 200 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> beſides the miſery <hi>I</hi> endured; and God bleſſed my trading when I began with a little ſtock again as <hi>I</hi> had left, having nothing to ſet me forward in trading from them, but words of promiſe. We were all made friends, but ſince <hi>I</hi> may curſe the day that ever <hi>I</hi> did truſt any ſuch former enemies to be reconciled friends again.</p>
               <p>For about the time as the Levellers did riſe againſt the Parliament, I having attained to a good flock of cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, and horſes, and trading, more then ever I was in before, my wife and <hi>I</hi> both living in a quiet condition, all former in juries forgiven by me to her and every one of them.</p>
               <p>And the ſpirit of God cauſed me to put out a little book concerning the preſent miſery of the times, both for Church and State. My wiſe and her frends that abaſed me before, brought greater calamity upon me then I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115635:32"/>before: Thus <hi>I</hi> was abuſed, and they banded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together againſt me. My own natural friends for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook me, God had ſo ordained it to try me, and puniſh me; for them that were formerly great pretended frends, became my utter enemies. <hi>I</hi> looked up ſtil towards God, his holy ſpirit ſtil guiding me with patience to endure it, and aſſuring me dayly more that the cauſe of my being thus abuſed by men and women, was becauſe <hi>I</hi> had caſt Gods meſſage behind my back. <hi>I</hi> often thinking how God puniſhed <hi>Jonah</hi> for his neglect, when God called him and ſent him to <hi>Nineveh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many of my beſt friends that loved me wel, would blame my Father for not taking my part; but God had ſuffered Satan to blind his eyes from the ſpirit of true diſcernment, as all natural men are, ſo that he did ſhew mee no favour, but added more affliction to me. Many would ſay to him, why doe you not ſeek to have him releaſed out of his miſery? If I ſhould doe ſo, ſaith he, he would be impriſoned for medling with King and Parliament-affaires; for I had been in priſon at <hi>Buckingham</hi> a little before, by ſome ſouldiers who rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thimſelves againſt me by falſe witneſſe, to make a prize of me for my horſes and goods, and carried mee from <hi>Buckingham</hi> to <hi>Alisbury</hi> to try me for my life, by falſe Articles as they had forged againſt me: But when I came to be tryed by a Councel of War, God gave me ſuch an undaunted ſpirit, that thoſe falſe witneſſes had not power to witneſſe againſt me: So <hi>I</hi> was ſet at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, having loſſe and hinderance of time.</p>
               <p>After theſe miſeries of impriſonment, and many more great troubles: in the mean time of my troubles, my wives friends ſetcht my beſt goods a way from my houſe, and ſome cattel, after <hi>I</hi> had forbid them to meddle with any thing: For when they ſaw they could not take my life away, they thought to make me run my Countrey; but God gave me much patience and courage; for <hi>I</hi> went to the houſe, and took four men with me: <hi>I</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded my goods, taking a cart and horſes to fetch
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115635:33"/>them in a peaceable manner, if I could have them ſo: But they denied me my goods, and my wife ſtood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me with railing words, and her Mother and one Sifter, the younger daughter did never ſpeak againſt me: So with much patience <hi>I</hi> went my way, and looked in their grounds, to ſee whether I could find any of my cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel there: Finding a Cow, and a young Bul that were mine, I took them away, to my houſe at <hi>Harburn</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The manner that they had taken them from me, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Lawes of God and man, was but a feloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous way of robbing me; for they owed me part of my Wives portion, as was due to mee long before that time.</p>
               <p>This was on the <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> On the <hi>Thurſday</hi> my wife knew that I would goe to <hi>Brimingham</hi>-market: her Father being from home, my wives Mother, her eldeſt Son, and my wife and her ſiſter <hi>Katherine,</hi> being fearful that I ſhould begin to trouble them, or bind them over by an order from the Juſtices, to anſwer at the Aſſizes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judge, for all the wrong they had done mee, they thought they had no other way to take, but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with me firſt, and ſo they did. For my brother-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law. his name is <hi>John Biſſel,</hi> met me at <hi>Brimingham</hi> on the Market-day, and arreſted me with flat felony, and ſo ſuddenly cauſed me to be thrown into the Dungeon; no Bail would be taken: All did condemn him ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully for it, yet wilfully and preſumptuouſly he did it. On the morrow I went to the Juſtices, the Juſtice could not perſwade him but he would take an oath of Felony againſt me; yet he could not deny but that the cattel were mine. After the Juſtice had examined thorowly the Witneſſes, he told him hanging was too good for him, and he ſhould dearly anſwer for it.</p>
               <p>Then when his Father came home out of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, for his Son did all in his Fathers name, he was almoſt out of his wits to heare what his Son had done; Fearing he ſhould be undone by it, preſently he made to the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115635:33"/>and to my Father and me and my friends, to take up the buſineſſe againe, and to keep me from going to priſon.</p>
               <p>This enſuing Bil of Divorcement was made after ſhe and her kindred had by Satans malice and their cruelty brought me into horrible perſecution and miſery. <hi>I</hi> may not now, for brevity-ſake, lay down the manner of it; but <hi>I</hi> hope in God in another Book <hi>I</hi> may, becauſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes I hope <hi>I</hi> ſhal have all the mercies of God ſhewed to me ſtil in remembrance.</p>
               <p>Her Father and ſhe coming on a Sabbath day where <hi>I</hi> was in priſon, gave me threatening words, and ſaid they were glad to ſee me there; and ſcoffing at me, her Father deſired that we were divorced. Wel ſaid <hi>I,</hi> pray you let it be ſo. His anſwer was, he would give forty pound upon the condition to have it ſo. I have witneſſe of it.</p>
               <p>At laſt they gave me good words: My deſire was for her to bring my daughter to me, that <hi>I</hi> might ſee her: She told me ſhe would not, and gave me very deſperate urging words to make a ſolemn Vow, that if ſhe did not bring my daughter between that time and <hi>Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> following, according to the Law of <hi>Moſes I</hi> would write her a bil of divorcement; if <hi>I</hi> could not get ink, <hi>I</hi> would write the firſt Copy of it with my owne blood, if <hi>I</hi> loft one of the joynts of my little finger on my left hand to do it, that all the reſt of my body might mourn for the loſſe of her that wanted grace to mourn for her ſelfe. Beſides this, <hi>I</hi> thought that many men might take example to put their wives away by divorcement with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any true deſert: And therefore, becauſe <hi>I</hi> intended to put the Bil of Divorcement in print, <hi>I</hi> would go ſuch a hard way, that none dare follow ſuch an example. Furthermore <hi>I</hi> deſired to know by a token if it were of God or no, that if ſhe came not with my child by <hi>Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday, I</hi> might neither eat nor ſleep with quietneſſe til <hi>I</hi> had disjoynted my ſelfe of the nail-joynt of my left hand, being the little fingers end. She came not, and that ſigne was fulfild; yet <hi>I</hi> did not doe it til above two
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115635:34"/>dayes after <hi>Wedneſday;</hi> and when <hi>I</hi> had done it, <hi>I</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome revelations from God to confirm it, ſuddenly I had a Revelation and a Viſion, that God had appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to be done, and that it was lawful for me to take another wife, as <hi>Hoſea</hi> did in a typical way: And it was ſhewed me by a Viſion between four, which was allotted for me, and how that <hi>I</hi> muſt ſpeak to one of the foure, and then ſpeak openly of it to others. This is near ſix yeares paft, and <hi>I</hi> beleeve the parties are unmarried ſtil. Let no man judge this to be madneſſe, but let them think if it be of God, it cannot be prevented.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Bill of Divorcement.</head>
                     <p>KNow this all my honeſt Chriſtian Neighbors, and all others whom it may concern, That I with much reverence and holy feare do call God to the recording and renewing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of this Obligation or Bill of Divorcement, which break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and violateth the band of Wedlock and Matrimony, and ſeparateth for ever ſhe that was formerly my Wife and me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder.</p>
                     <p>It is a very weighty matter, therefore it had need to bee underſtood, and throughly to be proved by the word of God, and the light of a good conſcience, which is that glittering ſword which ſtandeth drawn to ſlay every ſon and daughter of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> that either turneth to the right hand or to the leſt, either by hypecriſie or their own ſiniſter ends in ſuch weighty affaires as this.</p>
                     <p>I do therefore for ſeveral great cauſes, in the preſence of God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, which is my Redeemer, Creator, and Preſerver, whoſe powerful providence hath ſtill from time to time preſerved me from being ſwallowed up or deſtroyed by many great dangers, and ſeveral deſperate ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which the Devil hath formerly raiſed up againſt me, to bring me to an untimely death, without any juſt cauſe offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by me, whereof the ſaid <hi>Briget Biſſel,</hi> daughter of the the late ſaid <hi>Richard Biſſel,</hi> which is now dead, of the Pariſh of <hi>Yardlie,</hi> in the County of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> Ironmonger;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115635:34"/>the which ſaid <hi>Briget Biſſel,</hi> which was the married wife to me the ſaid <hi>John Sanders,</hi> whoſe dwelling was at <hi>Harburn,</hi> in the County of <hi>Stafford,</hi> Ironmonger, ſhe being a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to bring me into many borrible perſecutions, by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans malicious invention, and ſome of her neereſt kindreds counſel; for no other end, but for the witneſs of Jeſus, and his teſtimony, which hath carried me on by his holy Spirit of Propheſie.</p>
                     <p>Beſides, more then this miſery which ſhe and they brought upon me, ſhe and they have often urged me to be divorced from her for ever. I doe therefore, according to the Law of God, as he gave to <hi>Moſes,</hi> Deut. <hi>24.</hi> and Gods command to me, which cauſed me to write her this Bill of Divorcement af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner, and deliver it to her neere ſix yeares paſt, and now again it is renewed, deſiring that Gods mercy and forgiveneſſe may be extended to her for the forgiveneſs of her ſins, as well as for my ſelfe: And that it may pleaſe God, I humbly deſire upon the bended knees of my body and ſoule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affections, that the parting and breaking of this temporal wedlock, may cauſe a ſpiritual warriage to the Lamb Jeſus for us both; and that all profane and wicked perſons mouths may be ſtopt, that ſhall be apt to ſpeak againſt this, ſeeing it is permitted and ſo appointed by thee. O Lord raiſe me up ſpeedily by thy mercy and providence again, that ſo I may be able to take a godly fatherly care for my daughter, in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, Amen and ſo be it.</p>
                     <p>And ſhe is ever to be free from me to be any other mans wife, if it pleaſe God and her own conſcience: And the like releaſe is to me, if God and my own conſcience pleaſe; only ſome chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels and goods of mine which are in her keeping, contrary to my minde, at my demands to be at my requeſt when I pleaſe, if it be not otherwiſe agreed upon.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Theſe troubles were true ſignes to me, and gave mee cauſe to believe that God had appointed me as hee did <hi>Hoſea,</hi> Hoſ. 1.2. typically to take a wife of Fornications, becauſe the whole land had committed ſpiritual whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom againſt the Lord, and as the Prophet of God was to doe by Gods appointment, and to ſignifie how they had
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115635:35"/>divorced themſelves from the Lord by their idolatrous whoredomes, he was to divorce his wife for that as a figne.</p>
               <p>Truly Brethren, there is none can ſay but that the word of God is written as wel for our inſtruction, as it was to the natural ſeed of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for we are of <hi>Abraharis</hi> ſeed by Faith: And though the Scripture ſpeaks of ſuch things done then, yet there is a ſignification now of the ſame things to us.</p>
               <p>Our whole Land hath comitted ſpiritual whoredome againſt God. Firſt, in this manner, by breaking our ancient Covenant with God, to worſhip him in new fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled manners of their own invention, hating Gods old true way of worſhip, now there is no King, neither hath been this many dayes in <hi>England,</hi> neither true Sacrifice, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Secondly, our whole State being like the Nobility of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which brought no fruits of Reformation to God; but made High Altars to themſelves by Covetouſneſſe; which is idolatry and ſpiritual whoredome: And our being divided like them, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 10.2, 3.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, we may wel ſay our wars began, becauſe we would have no King to reign over us, for want of the fear of the Lord to guide us.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, who can ſay but they broke Covenant with God by ſwearing falſly to be true to the King and the Proteſtant Religion, and to work reformation in Church and State for true judgment: But in ſtead of being bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it is worſe, for it hath broke out like hem lock or wormwood in the furrowes of the Field, and hath tafted as bitter as gall, <hi>Amos</hi> 6.12. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 10.4, 7.</p>
               <p>And the death of King <hi>Charles</hi> is typified to be the King of <hi>Samaria,</hi> whom <hi>Hoſea</hi> propheſied ſhould be cut off as a foame on the factious water which the Devil caft out of his mouth to drown the woman, being meant the Church, in this time of new fangled worſhip, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical way of new opinions.</p>
               <p>If we ſee <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a's</hi> Propheſies to be fulfilled by the late
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115635:35"/>diſſolved Parliaments, and to be as true to us as they ſpeak of the natural <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> you cannot chuſe but believe it to be true in theſe things.</p>
               <p>And why then may not my troubles and croſſes, when I was forced by God, and their own violence againſt me, which could not be done without Gods permiſſion and ordination: Let no man dare, or preſume to judge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, but being done by Gods appointment, it did ſignifie theſe things as have befel our Nation between King and Parliament, by being divorced from God to follow their own corrupt wayes.</p>
               <p>My Wife came out of ſuch a Linage by her Fathers birth as <hi>Hoſea</hi> was to take his wife of for a further ſigne, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1. but <hi>I</hi> was ignorant of that when I married her; my love was never the leſſe to her; yet her Father had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the relation of all people to be a very honeſt deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man: But ſeeing my unhappy predeſtination was to be thus afflicted by ſhe that was my Wife, I look upon it no other way then this, it was becauſe I did not at the firſt forſake all theſe outward things of this life willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to goe on Gods meſſage. I am very ſorry that <hi>I</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbeare writing and laying open to the view of the world the wrong as I have received from her and their hands. Let no man judge the worſe of her or them for acting theſe ſtrange actions, or mee for relating of it; but let them all aſſure themſelves thus as heare of it. The Devil did not onely afflict <hi>Job</hi> by his wife, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans temptation by his friends, when he was in his great calamity; but the like inſtruments Satan can make uſe of any, let them be never ſo honeſt for natural parts, if God leave them to themſelves: <hi>But let every one watch and pray, leſt they fall into Satans temptations, and praiſe God for all the enjoyment of his benefits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any wil ſay, as many have done, that there can be no divocement lawful unleſſe it be for the act of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery: To give them an anſwer, look in <hi>Malachy</hi> 2.16. <hi>God hates putting away;</hi> but if ſo be thou muſt, ſuch ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities ought to be hid within ones own garment; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115635:36"/>if I doe know ſuch things, I will forbear ſpeaking of them to the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The humble Petition of</hi> John Sanders <hi>to the Lord Protector, Moſt humbly ſheweth,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat whereas the humble Petitioner have often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times on purpoſe many ſundry and long journeys to ſpeak with your Highneſſe, for the ſpace of above 3. yeares and a halfe; but none of theſe times could I find any opportunity by any of your Souldiers or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. I have at this time many grievances to eaſe and unburden my ſelfe of to your Highneſſe, which is the Head in chiefe: I having undergone much wrong by many ſeveral men, to the ſuſtaining of great loſſe both of goods and chattels, and other things: But concerning thoſe things, your humble Petitioner will keep ſilence at this time, committing all thoſe things to God, who hath kept my life from the rage of my enemies for the time paſt by his merciful providence, and ſo I truſt he wil for the time to come.</p>
               <p>My Lord, the cauſe of my complaint now at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time, after the many and ſundry journeys, and many loſſes and falſe impriſonments, which falſe boſome-friends, and falſe witneſſes have brought me to, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the witneſſe of Jeſus, which hath carried me on by his holy ſpirit to foretel things to come.</p>
               <p>About halfe a year before <hi>Worceſter</hi> fight, which was ſince you came to be Head Leader in chiefe of the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament Forces, the Lord compelled me openly to foretel how that King <hi>Charles</hi> would come with an Army into <hi>Worceſterſhire</hi> before <hi>Bartholomew</hi>-tide from <hi>Scotland</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament; and how that his taking up of Armes to maintaine the Scottiſh Presbytery Government would be the cauſe of the overthrow of his Army, if he fought: Theſe things God compelled me openly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in <hi>Brimingham,</hi> and at the Lady <hi>Graves,</hi> and many places more, and how Colonel <hi>Graves,</hi> the Ladies Son,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115635:36"/>would come in with him: I was caſt into great impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment and miſery by Satans malice and wicked men, til the very day of <hi>Worceſter</hi>-fight, and loſt all my time, trade, and ſtock, beſides all the miſery &amp; falſe impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>I</hi> underwent in ſeveral places. Som ſaid I was diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; others ſaid <hi>I</hi> was guided by the ſpirit of God; but in the preſence of God <hi>I</hi> ſpeak it, that I never knew my ſelfe at one time worſe then another, but it was the wil of God to carry me on in that manner: No man ever heard me ſpeak at thoſe times like one that had been di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted; but if Chriſt were ſo eſteemed, <hi>Mark</hi> 3. and <hi>Paul,</hi> let not me be aſhamed of that name by natural men, which are ſpiritually blind. Many witneſſes I could produce, that heard me foretel the manner and time of <hi>Worceſter</hi>-fight. When <hi>I</hi> was out of priſon, the ſpirit of the Lord cauſed mee to come fourſcore miles to ſpeak with your Highneſſe, and to tel you how that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtanding Parliament could not ſtand without they entred into a hallowed covenant with God at the Ark of his Teſtimony, for want of the true worſhip of Jeſus Chriſt, being found out and ſet above them, was the cauſe of Gods overthrowing them for their injuſtice and diviſion: But when I could not find an opportunity to declare Gods meſſage to your Highneſſe, I told Colonel <hi>Barkſtead</hi> theſe things, and ſhewed him writings, and told him what way the Church muſt and would be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>builded.</p>
               <p>Being then eaſed of my burden, I went home into my own Countrey again, and after that into <hi>Ireland,</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my ſelfe unfortunate: I carried iron ware to ſet up my trade there, and began it in <hi>Dublin;</hi> but the ſpirit of the Lord compelled me to come out of <hi>Ireland</hi> againe, to come up to <hi>London</hi> about ſix weeks before the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was diſſolved. I could not ſpeak with your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the Parliament was newly roſe about the Seamen; the ſpirit of God compelled me to make a Speech in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall before abundance of people concerning the Parliaments diſſolution about the ſhorteſt day in the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115635:37"/>yeare: And then before <hi>I</hi> could be eaſed of my burden, the ſpirit of God compelled me to goe to Colonel <hi>Barkeſtead,</hi> the Lieutenant of the Tower, to tel him Gods decree was ſo gone out againſt them for their covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, injuſtice, and diviſion, and to prefigure it by a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and a Revelation which I had ſeen before, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a white wand, and a bunch of filk colours, which were green, red, yellow, and black, and to tel him the meaning of it, by the appointment of God: Theſe things he cannot chuſe but witneſſe at this very day.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>I</hi> returned toward <hi>Warwickſhire</hi> again, and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified the ſame in many other places, and at <hi>Brimingham</hi> ſeveral Market dayes, in a ſtrange manner, to the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all that ſaw me, and griefe to my friends and kindred after the fleſh, and the greateſt griefe and terror of all was to my ſelfe, becauſe I was compelled by the dictates of Gods holy ſpirit to do it.</p>
               <p>And that very day that the Parliament was diſſolved, being <hi>Monday</hi> morning, I was cauſed by the ſpirit of God to goe from <hi>Harburn</hi> to <hi>Brimingham,</hi> which is two miles, to my great terrour and griefe, God is a witneſſe againſt me if <hi>I</hi> lie, and to hire the widow <hi>Weſtwoods</hi> ſon to goe with me to carry my beſt wearing cloathes for mee; and I was commanded of God to wear old cloaths and old ſhooes to <hi>Brimingham</hi> Townes end, and there to put my ſhooes off my feet, rent ſome ſeames of the old gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as I wore, and take a Carpenters Rule in my hand, the young man carrying my beſt raiment and old ſhooes before me, I making proclamation by the power of God, and his great Parliament of Heaven, and ſaying thus.</p>
               <p>If you ſhould ſee <hi>Ezekiel</hi> meaſuring the Town with a Rule, or ſeething a pot, and skimming off the skum, and nothing but water in it, or the holy men of God put off their ſhooes, or renting their garments, though the thing were commanded of God by them now as it hath formerly been, yet you would think they were mad, as the Jewes thought by <hi>Paul,</hi> ſo <hi>I</hi> know you think by me;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:115635:37"/>but it will be known otherwiſe: The Carpenters Rule that I had in my hand, was to ſignifie that Parliaments time of fitting was meaſured out to fit no longer: Then the ſeames of ſome of my old garments being rent, was to ſignifie their renting and tearing by diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The putting the old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ooes off my feet, <hi>I</hi> told them ſignified that they muſt caſt off their old natural ſinful affections from their hearts, and factious ſeditious ways, that their hearts might be made good ground, and they to become members of the true holy Church of God, which is hated by them.</p>
               <p>The cauſe of my ſpeaking of <hi>Ezechiels</hi> ſeething pot to be skummed off, I told them was the skum of factious mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Parliament-houſe, that were againſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Church-government, were then caſt out of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: Yet ſaid <hi>I,</hi> the fleſh and bones are left ſtil, and we ſhall not ſuddenly be eaſed of Taxes that oppreſſe the poor; and how that the power would be under one head ſuddenly, much like the power of a King, but not a King, which meant the Lord Protector.</p>
               <p>After all theſe things were ended, and done by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, by me his moſt unworthy ſervant <hi>John Saunders.</hi> I call God to witneſſe I would not have been hired to have done the like for a hundred pound then, nor would not now in a counterfeit way or manner. I never did the like before; ſome hypocritical people ſaid I counterfeited, and many phariſaical people, that ſay Prophecying, Viſions, and Revelations are ceaſed, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me a mad man. I praiſe God, for thoſe things, either diſſembling, counterfeiting, or natural madneſs, I have been alwayes free from.</p>
               <p>Then when theſe things were ended, I went and put on my better cloathing, and refreſhed my body by eating and drinking, I walked in the Towne civilly, in thoſe places where I had made thoſe ſpeeches, deſiring many of the honeſt civil people which I knew, that they ſhould not judge me diſtracted, or any other thing elſe, for thoſe words of wonder, or ſtrange poſtures, which I ſpake of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115635:38"/>and did. For I told them I did nothing but what I had a command from God, and was bound in the ſpirit thus to doe; yet I was no Ranter, or Quaker, or ſtrange O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinioniſt, and that you ſhal know by a good teſtimony ſhortly, if you take notice of it what <hi>I</hi> ſaid, and did at this time, or any other paſt but more eſpecially this ſtrange manner of that I now did, which you condemn me to be mad for doing: But within few dayes after I was thrown into <hi>Warwick</hi> Gaole by Satans malice and falſe witneſſe; for brevity-ſake at this time I wil forbear deſcribing the manner of it, I pray God forgive the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of that miſery, for there I had lamentable mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery about 30. dayes, or elſe ſuddenly I had come to the Lord Protector and Councel of State; but after I was at liberty, I did come ſuddenly after, the Lieutenant of the Tower knoweth it wel, and ſiince the laſt Sommer I went into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and wrote Letters unto Colonel <hi>Bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead,</hi> and came to him ſeveral times, as the beginning of the Book ſheweth.</p>
               <p>On <hi>New-yeares</hi> day in the morning 1654 in my ſleep I ſaw a Viſion, I being in <hi>London.</hi> Me thought I ſaw a great party of Parliament horſe drawed out of <hi>London</hi> going up <hi>Hoiborn, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge</hi> Road, and the Trumpets founding a very ſad ſolemn march as they went. I know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of them that was a ſouldier, I called to him and asked him what was the cauſe of their going out ſo ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily with ſuch a great party? He told me they did hear the King had a great Army <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge</hi> road coming toward <hi>London,</hi> and they went out to meet them and give them battel. I asked him what number the Parliament horſe were? He told me 7000. but the other J heard were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more. Me thoughts <hi>I</hi> would goe along with them to ſee them goe out of <hi>London,</hi> and I was very ſorry to think of ſo many of thoſe gallant men that would be ſlain, I overtaking the forefront of them; and before they were marched to <hi>Hide Park,</hi> I ſaw many men come running with ſpeed fromward <hi>Whitehall,</hi> with long white poles, and they were meaſuring the Land back again as
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115635:38"/>was taken away by the late War from the King, the which being done, to me ſignified peace betweene the Lord Protector and the King: So I awaked with much gladneſſe, praiſing God that he had ſent his Angel to ſhew me theſe things.</p>
               <p>Many more Viſious I have had lately to this effect. On the 14. of <hi>February</hi> 1654. being <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the night before I ſlept, I being perfectly awake, ſaw as it were in an apparition, the beginning of a work of new building in <hi>London</hi> for reformation of Church and State.</p>
               <p>A few nights after in <hi>February</hi> I ſaw another Viſion. I thought my ſelfe in <hi>Warwickſhire,</hi> at a place called <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> Pariſh, and I ſaw as <hi>I</hi> was walking over a piece of hard poore land, the braveſt hopeful green graſſe ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and young corne and hearbs in that barren land, all which gives me great teſtimonies of the Kings and Lord Protectors agreement, that peace may be eſtabliſhed in truth, and grace may abound and grow for the true nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of the Church.</p>
               <p>The firſt day of <hi>March,</hi> in ths morning <hi>I</hi> had another Viſion, how that there was a great plot or net lay for the Lord Protector concerning the Kings land. In the Kings ground <hi>I</hi> ſaw an apparition of one that told me by an audible voice of it: And <hi>I</hi> ſaw an apparition like a great net, to catch the Lord Protector. I was compelled by the dictates of God to write a letter concerning it, and carry it to the Lieutenant of the Tower. The tenth of <hi>March</hi> the dictates of Gods ſpirit cauſed me to write ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther letter, and carry it to the Tower, which if they did take notice of, it gave them warning of the riſing of men in ſeveral Counties ſuddenly upon it. Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is not of God, nor never will doe the King or any of his friends good.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
